<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17576681</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1934990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm402</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Genomics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites in human disease genes: mutation pattern, nucleotide structure and comparison of computational tools that predict their utilization</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>Emanuele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chivers</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000e1;lovi&#x0010d;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Jana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>Adrian R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vo&#x00159;echovsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>Igor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>1</sup>International Centre for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology, Padriciano 99, 34012 Trieste, Italy, <sup>2</sup>University of Southampton School of Medicine, Division of Human Genetics, Southampton SO16 6YD, UK and <sup>3</sup>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 1 Bungtown Road, Cold Spring Harbor, NY 11724, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. <phone>+44 2380 796425</phone><fax>+44 2380 794264</fax><email>i.vorechovsky@soton.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>4250</fpage><lpage>4263</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Despite a growing number of splicing mutations found in hereditary diseases, utilization of aberrant splice sites and their effects on gene expression remain challenging to predict. We compiled sequences of 346 aberrant 5&#x02032;splice sites (5&#x02032;ss) that were activated by mutations in 166 human disease genes. Mutations within the 5&#x02032;ss consensus accounted for 254 cryptic 5&#x02032;ss and mutations elsewhere activated 92 <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss. Point mutations leading to cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation were most common in the first intron nucleotide, followed by the fifth nucleotide. Substitutions at position +5 were exclusively G&#x0003e;A transitions, which was largely attributable to high mutability rates of C/G&#x0003e;T/A. However, the frequency of point mutations at position +5 was significantly higher than that observed in the Human Gene Mutation Database, suggesting that alterations of this position are particularly prone to aberrant splicing, possibly due to a requirement for sequential interactions with U1 and U6 snRNAs. Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were best predicted by computational algorithms that accommodate nucleotide dependencies and not by weight-matrix models. Discrimination of intronic 5&#x02032;ss from their authentic counterparts was less effective than for exonic sites, as the former were intrinsically stronger than the latter. Computational prediction of exonic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss was poor, suggesting that their activation critically depends on exonic splicing enhancers or silencers. The authentic counterparts of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss were significantly weaker than the average human 5&#x02032;ss. The development of an online database of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss will be useful for studying basic mechanisms of splice-site selection, identifying splicing mutations and optimizing splice-site prediction algorithms.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Mutations that influence pre-mRNA splicing represent a substantial proportion of gene alterations leading to Mendelian disorders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>). cDNA-based mutation studies of disease genes that have a large number of introns showed that splicing mutations accounted for about half of mutated alleles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>). In contrast, estimates derived from DNA-based mutation screening designed to scan coding regions and flanking intronic sequences have generally been lower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). As a significant fraction of mutated alleles in both recessive and dominant conditions has not been identified, and the availability of RNA samples from affected individuals and their families is often problematic, the overall contribution of intronic alterations acting at the level of pre-mRNA splicing could be substantial. In addition to single-gene disorders, DNA variants that influence splicing may modify the risk of developing complex diseases and their phenotypic manifestations, but the overall role of this variability in the pathogenesis of such conditions is only beginning to be explored (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5 B6 B7 B8">5&#x02013;8</xref>).</p><p>The most common consequence of splicing mutations is skipping of one or more exons, followed by the activation of aberrant 5&#x02032; (donor) splice sites (5&#x02032;ss), 3&#x02032; (acceptor) splice sites (3&#x02032;ss) and full intron retention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>). Mutation-induced aberrant splice sites found in disease genes often involve disruption of the consensus sequence of the authentic sites, while activating a cryptic splice site nearby. However, aberrant splice sites can also be generated by mutations that create splice-site consensus sequences. As described earlier (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>), we refer to these aberrant splice sites as cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic>, respectively, even though the distinction between cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> sites may occasionally be vague, because disruption of the authentic site can also create a new splice site consensus.</p><p>Cryptic 3&#x02032;ss are preferentially located in exons whereas <italic>de novo</italic> 3&#x02032;ss usually reside in introns, which has been attributed to splicing signal sequences upstream of the 3&#x02032;ss that are required for selection of acceptor sites, including the polypyrimidine tract (PPT) and the branch point sequence (BPS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>). In contrast to cryptic 3&#x02032;ss, cryptic 5&#x02032;ss have a similar frequency distribution in exons and introns and their number decreases with increasing distance from the authentic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). The human 5&#x02032;ss consensus sequence is MAG|GURAGU (M is A or C; R is purine), spanning from position &#x02212;3 to position +6 relative to the exon&#x02013;intron junction. This sequence is critical but often insufficient for accurate 5&#x02032;ss recognition, and may require auxiliary sequences in both introns and exons. These sequences can repress or activate splicing and are referred to as splicing silencers or enhancers, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13 B14 B15 B16 B17">13&#x02013;17</xref>). The complementarity of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus to the 5&#x02032; end of U1 small nuclear RNA (snRNA) exerts a dominant effect on 5&#x02032;ss selection, but auxiliary sequences may exhibit a more prominent role in selection of competing 5&#x02032;ss with lower base-pairing complementarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>). In addition, the intrinsic structural properties of the RNA molecule may hinder 5&#x02032;ss availability for basal splicing factors, thus controlling splicing efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20 B21 B22">20&#x02013;22</xref>). Moreover, 5&#x02032;ss selection can also be influenced by the presence of sequence motifs specific for RNA-binding proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>) and by the rate at which the pre-mRNA is transcribed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>).</p><p>A variety of methods have been used to computationally predict the 5&#x02032;ss strength and recognition, including nucleotide frequency matrices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>), machine-learning approaches and neural networks (NNs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>) and methods employing putative base-pairing interactions of 5&#x02032;ss with U1 snRNP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28 B29 B30">28&#x02013;30</xref>) and interdependence between adjacent or more distant positions of the splicing consensus sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). Exon-prediction algorithms that take into account protein-coding information may perform better than those that rely only on signals present in the splice sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>). However, it is unknown which models best predict the localization of cryptic or <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss that were activated <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>In the present study, we compiled nucleotide sequences of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss that have been reported previously in human disease genes since the first description of disease-causing aberrant splice sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33 B34 B35">33&#x02013;35</xref>). This resource is being made available to the public through an online retrieval and submission tool termed DBASS5 (<underline>d</underline>ata<underline>b</underline>ase of <underline>a</underline>berrant <underline>5</underline>&#x02032; <underline>s</underline>plice <underline>s</underline>ites). In addition, we provide a detailed characterization of the underlying mutation pattern, a comparison of the nucleotide composition of aberrant and corresponding authentic 5&#x02032;ss, and we evaluate the performance of computational tools that predict their utilization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Compilation of mutation-induced aberrant 5&#x02032;ss in human disease genes</title><p>Aberrant 5&#x02032;ss were identified by searching home pages of peer-reviewed journals and PubMed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi</ext-link>). They were included in the database and selected for further analysis if (i) they resulted from disease-causing or -predisposing mutations or variants in human genes; (ii) aberrant RNA products spliced to new 5&#x02032;ss were verified by nucleotide sequencing; and (iii) their sequences or reliable identifiers were published in peer-reviewed journals between 1981 and January 2007. We also included 22 cases of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss that were confirmed by minigene assays with wild-type and mutated reporter constructs transfected into mammalian cells, but from which patients&#x02019; RNA samples were not available. These criteria were similar to those used for a recently published analysis of aberrant 3&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p>Aberrant 5&#x02032;ss were manually validated by mapping the information in the literature to sequences in the Human Genome Project databases. Nucleotide sequences of authentic, mutated and aberrant 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032;ss are available online in the Database of Aberrant Splice Sites <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dbass.org.uk/">http://www.dbass.org.uk/</ext-link>, which consists of the recently described DBASS3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) and the newly developed DBASS5.</p></sec><sec><title>Computational methods to predict aberrant 5&#x02032;ss</title><p>Validated sequences of aberrant and corresponding authentic 5&#x02032;ss were used as input files for seven publicly available splice-site prediction algorithms. The Shapiro and Senapathy (S&#x00026;S) matrix is based on nucleotide frequencies of 5&#x02032;ss and assumes independence between individual positions of the 9-nt consensus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>). The S&#x00026;S matrix scores were computed using an online tool available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ast.bioinfo.tau.ac.il/SpliceSiteFrame.htm">http://ast.bioinfo.tau.ac.il/SpliceSiteFrame.htm</ext-link>. To take into account known dependencies between adjacent and non-adjacent positions of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus, the compiled sequences were analysed using the first-order Markov model (MM) and the maximum entropy (ME) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The former method considers dependencies between adjacent positions, whereas the latter model approximates short-sequence motif distributions with the ME distribution and may include dependencies between non-adjacent as well as adjacent positions. The maximum dependence decomposition model (MDD) is a decision-tree approach that accentuates the strongest dependencies in the early branches of the tree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>). The MM, ME, MDD and weight-matrix (WMM) scores, which extract single nucleotide probabilities for each position from a training set (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>), were computed using online tools at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genes.mit.edu/burgelab/maxent/Xmaxentscan_scoreseq_acc.html">http://genes.mit.edu/burgelab/maxent/Xmaxentscan_scoreseq_acc.html</ext-link>. The HBond algorithm, which analyses individual hydrogen-bonding patterns to the U1 snRNA 5&#x02032; end irrespective of nucleotide frequencies and assumes that the threshold values for U1 snRNP binding are influenced by specific SR proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>) was computed using a web application available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uni-duesseldorf.de/rna/html/hbond_score.php">http://www.uni-duesseldorf.de/rna/html/hbond_score.php</ext-link>. The NN algorithm is a machine-learning approach that recognizes sequence patterns once it is trained with DNA sequences encompassing authentic splice sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>). We used the NN splice site predictor NNSPLICE (v. 0.9) at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fruitfly.org/seq_tools/splice.html">http://www.fruitfly.org/seq_tools/splice.html</ext-link>. The free energy (&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>) of predicted 5&#x02032;ss/U1 base-pairing was computed using OligoArrayAux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>), which is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinfo.rpi.edu/applications/hybrid/Oligo-ArrayAux.php">http://www.bioinfo.rpi.edu/applications/hybrid/Oligo-ArrayAux.php</ext-link>. Finally, the number of H bonds (#H) between 5&#x02032;ss and U1 was computed using a web tool at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ast.bioinfo.tau.ac.il/SpliceSiteFrame.htm">http://ast.bioinfo.tau.ac.il/SpliceSiteFrame.htm</ext-link>.</p><p>To compare the strength of aberrant or authentic 5&#x02032;ss with a large number of human 5&#x02032;ss, we used the sequences of 8415 5&#x02032;ss reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). The non-parametric Wilcoxon&#x02013;Mann&#x02013;Whitney rank test (Stat-200, v. 2.01, Biosoft Ltd., UK) was employed to test the significance of score differences between authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss in each category.</p></sec><sec><title>DBASS5 construction</title><p>DBASS5 (<underline>d</underline>ata<underline>b</underline>ase of <underline>a</underline>berrant <underline>5</underline>&#x02032; <underline>s</underline>plice <underline>s</underline>ites) is an online retrieval and submission tool for mutation-induced aberrant 5&#x02032;ss available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dbass.org.uk/5/">http://www.dbass.org.uk/5/</ext-link>, complementing a recently described sister database of aberrant 3&#x02032;ss, termed DBASS3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>). The web application was created using the Microsoft ASP and ASP.Net server technology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.asp.net">http://www.asp.net</ext-link>), and Microsoft SQL Server database software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.microsoft.com/sql/">http://www.microsoft.com/sql/</ext-link>). In addition to aberrant 5&#x02032;ss induced by disease-associated germline and somatic mutations, DBASS5 contains naturally occurring DNA variants that were shown to modify both the relative expression of RNA products spliced to alternative 5&#x02032;ss and the disease predisposition. Polymorphisms that control exon skipping levels or full intron retention events have not been included in DBASS5.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Mutations that activate aberrant 5&#x02032;ss</title><p>An exhaustive search for previously published aberrant 5&#x02032;ss identified 305 unique aberrant 5&#x02032;ss in 166 genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). They were generated by a total of 26 deletions/duplications, 3 insertions, 2 complex alterations and 315 point mutations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). These alterations were described in a total of 264 publications.
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of cryptic or <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032; splice sites</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Exon</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Intron</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere (&#x02018;<italic>de novo</italic>&#x02019;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere (&#x02018;<italic>de novo</italic>&#x02019;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All mutations</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of genes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of phenotypes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032; ss (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (35.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (13.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (38.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (13.3)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of unique 5&#x02032;ss (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (37.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (14.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (33.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (15.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">305 (100.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss affecting terminal exons (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median distance (nt) between authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in the reading frame for unique aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><p><sup>a</sup>The number of pseudoexons (cryptic exons) was 31 (9.0% of all reported aberrant 5&#x02032;ss and 10.1% of unique aberrant 5&#x02032;ss).</p></fn><fn id="TF2"><p><sup>b</sup>The distribution of the reading frame changes among unique aberrant 5&#x02032;ss (excl. cryptic exons) was not significantly different from that expected (<italic>P</italic> = 0.75).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Summary of mutations leading to aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of cryptic or <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032; splice sites</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Exon</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Intron</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere (&#x02018;<italic>de novo</italic>&#x02019;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere (&#x02018;<italic>de novo</italic>&#x02019;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All mutations</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of deletions/duplications</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of insertions</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of complex mutations</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of single-nucleotide substitutions</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type nucleotide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;G</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mutated nucleotide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;G</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of GT-creating mutations (%)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (58)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (51)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (50)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (70)</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (55)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The number of reported cryptic 5&#x02032;ss was almost three times higher than the number of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were usually activated by single-nucleotide substitutions of guanosine (G) residues, which were &#x0223c;3-times more common than mutations of the remaining nucleotides (177 versus 57, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Conversely, substituting adenosines accounted for almost every other point mutation. Among single-nucleotide substitutions leading to <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss, cytosine was the most frequently mutated nucleotide (32/81, 40%). In contrast, no <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss have thus far been reported to be created by a point mutation introducing cytosine (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>The overall distribution of unique point mutations within the 9-nt consensus sequence was highly non-random both for cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). For cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, point mutations were most common at the highly conserved position +1 relative to the natural intron/exon junctions (39.4%). Interestingly, the second most frequently mutated position was the fifth intron nucleotide (21.6%), followed by positions +2 (14.7%) and &#x02013;1 (14.3%). Point mutations at positions +3, +4, +6 and &#x02212;2 each accounted for &#x0003c;3% of all the single-nucleotide substitutions. In contrast to cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, the most frequent point mutations resulting in <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss were at the highly conserved first (28%) and second (34%) intron nucleotides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Single-nucleotide substitutions at position +5 were found only in 5/81 (6%) unique <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss as opposed to 50/234 unique cryptic 5&#x02032;ss (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 8.6, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003). The ratio of point mutations in cryptic over <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss in the authentic and new 9-nt consensus, respectively, was highest for position +5 (10.0), followed by position &#x02212;1 (5.5) and +1 (4.1), with an average ratio for all positions of 2.9.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Distribution of point mutations activating cryptic and/or creating <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss. The <italic>x</italic>-axis shows the position of point mutations in the 9-nucleotide 5&#x02032;ss consensus relative to the natural exon&#x02013;intron junctions (cryptic 5&#x02032;ss) or to the newly created exon&#x02013;intron boundary (<italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss). The total number of point mutations at each position of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus is shown on the <italic>y</italic>-axis. Grey bars denote the number of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss; black bars denote the number of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss. The corresponding number of splicing mutations logged in the HGMD was 11, 51, 320, 1445, 456, 163, 63, 347 and 46 for positions &#x02013;3 through +6, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f1"/></fig></p><p>The overall proportion of point mutations in patients with aberrant 5&#x02032;ss that created the 5&#x02032;GT consensus was &#x0223c;55% (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Newly created 5&#x02032;GT dinucleotides were utilized by the spliceosome in 100% of the observed cases. In contrast, although mutations generating 3&#x02032;AG dinucleotides found in individuals with aberrant 3&#x02032;ss are also present in about half of the cases, only &#x0223c;95% are used <italic>in vivo</italic>, owing to the presence of &#x02018;AG exclusion zones&#x02019; downstream of the BPS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>).</p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref> show the breakdown of point mutations by nucleotide and by highly conserved positions of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus. Transitions (R-to-R or Y-to-Y, Y is pyrimidine), which account for 62.5% of point mutations in human disease genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), were found in 58.7% of cases (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Comparison of mutations in highly conserved positions of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus with those expected based on previously published mononucleotide mutation rates corrected for a number of confounding effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>) suggested that the biased distribution is unlikely to be fully explained by differential mutability (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>; <italic>P</italic> = 0.002 and 4.3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup> for position +1 and +2, respectively). However, comparison with the published dinucleotides rates that take into account nearest-neighbour effects no longer showed a significant <italic>P</italic>-value for position +1, consistent with a severe block of splicing following mutations to any nucleotide (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>). Nevertheless, the distribution of point mutations at position +2 was still unlikely to be fully explained by differential mutabilities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.035), raising the possibility that the observed under-representation of +2C/A among cryptic 5&#x02032;ss may be attributed to higher residual levels of accurately spliced pre-mRNAs with 5&#x02032;GC or 5&#x02032;GA dinucleotides. This would be consistent with a previously observed +2T&#x0003e;+2C&#x0003e;+2A&#x0003e;+2G hierarchy in splicing efficiency (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>) and with efficient recognition of the 0.56% of mammalian introns that have 5&#x02032;GC-3&#x02032;AG splice sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>). Finally, the distribution of point mutations at positions +1 and +2 and that for all splicing mutations in the Human Gene Mutation Database (HGMD, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/index.php">http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/index.php</ext-link>) were not significantly different (<italic>P</italic> = 0.77 for position +1 and <italic>P</italic> = 0.15 for position +2, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). This suggests that the mutation spectrum of the 5&#x02032;GT dinucleotide is similar for aberrant 5&#x02032;ss and exon skipping events, which represent the bulk of HGMD entries.
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Breakdown by type of point mutations leading to aberrant 5&#x02032;ss</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1">Mutated nucleotide</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wild-type nucleotide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (11.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (7.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (34.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (11.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (15.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (5.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The number of point mutations for each nucleotide substitution is followed by a percentage in parentheses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Number of single-nucleotide substitutions in highly conserved positions of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus that resulted in cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Observed numbers for cryptic 5&#x02032;ss</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expected<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF4"><sup>b</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of cryptic 5&#x02032; splice site</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exon</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intron</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Point mutations at position IVS-1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02212;1G&#x0003e;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02212;1G&#x0003e;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02212;1G&#x0003e;T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Point mutations at position IVS+1</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+1G&#x0003e;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (1024)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.3 (60.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+1G&#x0003e;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (273)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9 (12.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+1G&#x0003e;T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (411)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9 (18.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Point mutations at position IVS+2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+2T&#x0003e;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (270)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5 (16.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+2T&#x0003e;G</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (144)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (9.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+2T&#x0003e;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (121)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (8.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Point mutations at position IVS+5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+5G&#x0003e;C</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+5G&#x0003e;T</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;+z5G&#x0003e;A</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF3"><p><sup>a</sup>The numbers in parentheses refer to all splicing mutations logged in the Human Gene Mutation Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>). (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/hoho2/php">http://www.hgmd.cf.ac.uk/ac/hoho2/php</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="TF4"><p><sup>b</sup>The expected numbers were calculated from the relative mononucleotide mutability rates corrected for codon frequencies and other confounding effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>). The expected numbers calculated from the previously published estimates of the relative substitution rates at the dinucleotide level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>) are in parentheses in the same table column.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec><title>Frequent occurrence of IVS+5G mutations leading to cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation</title><p>Interestingly, all point mutations at position +5 of authentic 5&#x02032;ss that activated cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were substitutions of G, and not any other nucleotide (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), raising the possibility that 5&#x02032;ss with +5G are more susceptible to aberrant splice-site activation than 5&#x02032;ss with +5H (non-G). However, assuming &#x0223c;78% occupancy of this nucleotide in human 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and a G/C substitution rate of &#x0223c;70% derived from the HGMD data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>), the expected number of +5H substitutions among authentic sites whose mutation induces cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation would only be &#x0223c;4 in our dataset and not significantly different from zero (<italic>P</italic> = 0.1, Fisher's exact test). A prominent influence of differential mutability rates on the mutation spectrum was also supported by the observed predominance of +5G&#x0003e;A transitions over transversions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). In addition, the distribution of point mutations activating cryptic 5&#x02032;ss was significantly different from that resulting in <italic>de novo</italic> sites (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), with the latter showing peaks in the most conserved positions +1 and +2 and exclusive +5A&#x0003e;G transitions relative to new 5&#x02032;ss that were located both in exons (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>) or introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46 B47 B48">46&#x02013;48</xref>). However, unique point mutations in the 9-nt consensus logged in the HGMD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>) and in our sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) had significantly different distributions (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 27.7, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0005), with position +5 clearly overrepresented in our dataset (&#x0223c;22% versus &#x0223c;12%). This suggests that the mutation spectra underlying cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation and exon skipping events are distinct.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss generated by point mutations at position IVS+5. (<bold>A</bold>) Nucleotide composition of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activated by point mutations at position +5 (upper panel) and their authentic counterparts (lower panel). Sequence alignments of unique 5&#x02032;ss were analysed by a pictogram utility available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genes.mit.edu/pictogram.html">http://genes.mit.edu/pictogram.html</ext-link>. The size of a pictogram character is proportional to the frequency of each nucleotide, with the most frequent at the top. The percentage of the most frequent nucleotide is shown above or below each panel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f2"/></fig></p><p>A search for literature reports of point mutations that produce either aberrant 5&#x02032;ss activation or exon skipping in the same 5&#x02032;ss consensus revealed several discordant cases. For example, the <italic>FBN1</italic> substitution IVS46+5G&#x0003e;A resulted in cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation 33-nt downstream of the authentic exon&#x02013;intron junction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>), whereas the IVS46+1G&#x0003e;A mutation caused exon 46 skipping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>). Similarly, the <italic>PTEN</italic> mutation IVS7+1G&#x0003e;A activated a cryptic 5&#x02032;ss 75-nt downstream of the authentic exon&#x02013;intron boundary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>), whereas mutation IVS7+2T&#x0003e;G in the same 5&#x02032;ss led exclusively to exon 7 skipping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>). In the latter case, IVS7+2T&#x0003e;G creates a putative splicing silencer containing the AGGG motif, which may prevent activation of the downstream cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, whereas IVS7+1G&#x0003e;A results in no consecutive Gs in the 5&#x02032;ss consensus.</p><p>The presence of IVS+5H in authentic 5&#x02032;ss, which is not predicted to base-pair with U1 or U6 snRNAs, was proposed to be compensated by having G at the last exon position (&#x02013;1G) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>). The &#x02013;1G can base-pair to U1 snRNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>) and is almost completely conserved (97.5%) in IVS+5H 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>). The +5/&#x02212;1 association was confirmed with a large sample of homologous human-mouse 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>). In our dataset, only 18/35 (51%) of unique authentic 5&#x02032;ss that were repressed by mutations of IVS+5G in favour of a cryptic 5&#x02032;ss had -1G. This percentage is significantly (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 10.9, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) lower than for a large set of authentic 5&#x02032;ss (5142/6716, &#x0223c;77%). In addition to position &#x02013;1, adenosine &#x02013;2 was less frequent in our sample (31%; 11/24) as compared with 57% in average 5&#x02032;ss (3830/6716, <italic>P</italic> = 0.002), while the number of uracils at position +6 was higher (25/35; 71% versus 3415/6716; 51%; &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 5.1, <italic>P</italic> = 0.02). These results are consistent with previously described +5 dependencies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>) and suggest that authentic 5&#x02032;ss that are susceptible to IVS+5 mutations are less likely to make sufficient contacts between positions &#x02013;1/&#x02013;2 and their interacting factors, but may exhibit stronger putative base-pairing interactions between U1/U6 snRNAs and intron position +6.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of computational tools to predict mutation-induced aberrant 5&#x02032;ss <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> shows the relative representation of each nucleotide in the consensus sequence of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss (upper panels) and the corresponding authentic sites (lower panels). The consensus sequence of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss had lower proportions of conserved residues than for authentic 5&#x02032;ss at each position, except for the invariant position +1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>A). This difference was much reduced in <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss, in which conserved nucleotides at positions +3 through +6 had even higher frequencies than those in their authentic counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>B). Sequence alignments of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> sites generated in exons and introns are shown in Supplementary <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1 F2 F3">Figures 1&#x02013;3</xref> together with their authentic counterparts.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Sequence alignment of authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss. Sequence alignment of cryptic (<bold>A</bold>, upper panel) and <italic>de novo</italic> (<bold>B</bold>, upper panel) 5&#x02032;ss with their matching authentic counterparts (lower panels). The nucleotide alignments were analysed by a pictogram utility as in Figure 2. The size of a pictogram character is proportional to the frequency of each nucleotide, with the most common at the top. The percentage of the most frequent nucleotides in aberrant and authentic sites is shown above and below each panel, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f3"/></fig></p><p>Apart from &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> and #H between 5&#x02032;ss and U1 snRNA, we used seven different algorithms that predict utilization of 5&#x02032;ss in multiple sequences and are publicly available (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A,B). Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss had significantly lower scores with each algorithm, lower #H and higher &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> than their authentic, wild-type counterparts. Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were most effectively discriminated from the authentic sites by the ME model, followed by MDD and MM algorithms. <italic>P</italic>-values obtained for the HBond and NN scores were higher, even when we disregarded cryptic 5&#x02032;ss with non-canonical 5&#x02032;ss dinucleotides to obtain the scores and replaced them with group means. All these models clearly outperformed the matrix-based prediction scores&#x02014;S&#x00026;S and WMM. The #H and &#x00394;<italic>G</italic> values gave the poorest, albeit still significant discrimination. The weakness of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss was well illustrated by a shift of the #H peak frequency from seven in the authentic counterparts to six in the cryptic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C).
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Comparison of computational tools to predict aberrant 5&#x02032;ss. (<bold>A</bold>) cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss. S&#x00026;S, Shapiro-Senapathy matrix score; ME, Maximum Entropy model; MDD, maximal dependence decomposition model; MM, First-order Markov model; WMM, weight matrix model; Hbond, HBond score; #H, number of H bonds; &#x00394;G, predicted free energy; NN, neural network model. <italic>P-</italic>values of the Wilcoxon&#x02013;Mann&#x02013;Whitney rank tests comparing authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss are shown in parentheses for each algorithm. Pseudoexons were not included in this comparison. (<bold>C</bold>), #H distribution in cryptic/<italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss and their authentic counterparts. The expected #H distribution of natural 5&#x02032;ss (closed diamonds) was calculated from the #H frequencies observed for a large collection of human 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>). (<bold>D</bold>), The proportion of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss with equal or higher splice-site scores than their authentic counterparts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f4"/></fig></p><p>In contrast to cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss were not distinguished from their authentic counterparts by any of the tested algorithms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B). Although the number of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss was smaller than cryptic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), random selections of the same number of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss and their comparison with authentic sites gave consistently significant discrimination with several algorithms (data not shown), indicating that computational prediction of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss is poor. However, newly created 5&#x02032;ss activating pseudoexons had higher ME scores than the remaining <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (8.66 &#x000b1; 3.00 versus 6.07 &#x000b1; 4.83, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0002) or the remaining intronic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>, <italic>P</italic> = 0.002). The corresponding 3&#x02032;ss of these pseudoexons were slightly stronger than intronic <italic>de novo</italic> 3&#x02032;ss (ME scores 6.79 &#x000b1; 3.39 versus 5.24 &#x000b1; 4.50, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) ascertained previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), but were not significantly different from exonic <italic>de novo</italic> 3&#x02032;ss or their authentic counterparts. Thus, activation of cryptic exons through <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss use requires their high strength and may be facilitated by intrinsically stronger decoy 3&#x02032;ss across the newly formed exon.
<table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the strength of wild-type authentic, mutated and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Location of aberrant 5&#x02032; splice sites <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TF5"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Exon</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Intron</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Mutation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere (&#x02018;<italic>de novo</italic>&#x02019;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">In the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus (cryptic)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elsewhere ('<italic>de novo</italic>')</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">All mutations</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shapiro and Senapathy matrix score (S&#x00026;S)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.3 (8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6 (9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.6 (9.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0 (8.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.8 (9.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.7 (10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3 (8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.7 (10.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.8</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;13</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6.1</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.6</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;11</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4 (11.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.6 (9.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.1 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7 (7.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7 (12.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum entropy model (ME)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (5.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (4.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (4.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.8</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;21</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.8</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.6</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.8 (6.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4 (6.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum-dependence decomposition model (MDD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4 (3.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.9 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (4.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2 (4.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;18</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.1</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.001</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.0</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 (5.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9 (2.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">First-order Markov model (MM)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (2.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (3.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (3.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.6</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;19</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.4</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.016</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.9</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (4.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight matrix model (WMM)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4 (3.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.4</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6.2</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.020</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.8</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (4.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HBond score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.7 (2.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6 (3.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4 (2.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (2.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8 (3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (3.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (3.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.4</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;18</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.0</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.015</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.8</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free energy (&#x00394;G)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.8 (2.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.8 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.5 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.7 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.7 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>3.9 (2.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.5 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>4.7 (2.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.6 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>4.6 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.5</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;9</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9.3</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.2</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>2.7 (2.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.8 (2.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>1.9 (1.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>5.7 (2.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x02212;</bold>3.1 (2.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of H bonds (#H)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.7</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.1</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7 (1.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (1.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3 (1.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neural network (NN)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AU (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 (0.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AB (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 (0.35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 (0.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 (0.39)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.2</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.4</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.1</bold>&#x02009;<bold>&#x000d7;</bold>&#x02009;<bold>10<sup>&#x02212;15</sup></bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Means and standard deviations (SD) of splice-site prediction scores for wild-type authentic (AU) and aberrant (AB) 5&#x02032;ss are followed by the <italic>P</italic>-values (corrected for ties) of the Wilcoxon&#x02013;Mann&#x02013;Whitney rank tests comparing AB and AU. A small number of missing values for the HBond and NN scores due to non-canonical nucleotides at positions +1 and +2 were treated as a group mean. <italic>P</italic>-values below 0.05 were considered significant and are shown in bold. The splice-site strength for authentic 5&#x02032;ss with mutations (MU) is shown only for algorithms that score non-canonical 5&#x02032;ss.</p></fn><fn id="TF5"><p><sup>a</sup>Pseudoexons were not included in this comparison.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>We then tested each computational method separately for aberrant 5&#x02032;ss in exons and introns (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>). Although cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in exons were best discriminated by the ME scores, the lowest <italic>P</italic>-values for cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in introns were achieved by the NN model. To test whether this could be explained by having to disregard 5&#x02032;GC splice sites for the NN method in both datasets and replace them by group means, we recalculated the NN and ME scores after removing 5&#x02032;GC splice sites, but we obtained a similar result (<italic>P</italic> = 1.2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;12</sup> versus 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>, respectively). Authentic counterparts of intronic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss were intrinsically weak and therefore less likely to challenge newly created competitors. However, this was not evident for exonic <italic>de novo</italic> sites, strongly suggesting that their activation is more reliant on splicing regulatory sequences in exons rather than on the intrinsic strength of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>). The overall performance of ME, MDD, MM, HBond and NN models for the whole set of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss was very similar, with minimal differences in <italic>P</italic>-values. Finally, mutated authentic 5&#x02032;ss were on average weaker than cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, confirming an earlier observation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>). Again, the lowest <italic>P</italic>-values of the non-parametric test were observed for the ME model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref> and data not shown). Thus, as shown for 3&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), the ME algorithm discriminated best both wild-type and mutated authentic 5&#x02032;ss from cryptic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>), thus providing a method of choice for computational prediction of aberrant splice sites.</p><p>Next, we carried out pair-wise comparisons of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss with their authentic counterparts. For each computational algorithm, we determined the proportion of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss that showed equal or higher scores than their respective wild-type authentic sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). This proportion was on average significantly higher for <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss than for cryptic 5&#x02032;ss and roughly reflected the ability of each method to discriminate between aberrant 5&#x02032;ss and their authentic counterparts. The percentage of exonic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss with equal or higher scores than their authentic counterparts was lowest for the ME algorithm (10.5%). For intronic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, the same proportion was lowest for the NN method (14.4%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>D). Using the best-performing algorithms, &#x0223c;12.3% of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were computationally stronger than their wild-type authentic counterparts, yet they were used <italic>in vivo</italic> only if the wild-type 5&#x02032;ss consensus was inactivated or weakened by mutation. This underscores the importance of factors that repress utilization of decoy splice sites that are present in excess over natural sites in the genome.</p><p>Importantly, the authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were significantly weaker than a large collection of 8415 natural 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>), with the ME scores of 7.75 &#x000b1; 2.50 and 8.37 &#x000b1; 2.08, respectively (<italic>P</italic> = 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>; Wilcoxon&#x02013;Mann&#x02013;Whitney rank test). The distribution of #H in the authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss and natural 5&#x02032;ss was also significantly different (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02, &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 13.5, 5 df for 4&#x02013;9 #H), with a maximum difference at 8 #H (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>C). The relative weakness of the authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss is consistent with the notion that mutations in less conserved positions of stronger 5&#x02032;ss produce, on average, higher amounts of natural transcripts and less severe phenotypes than identical alterations in intrinsically weaker 5&#x02032;ss.</p><p>The predicted strengths of authentic sites that were mutated at position +5 were significantly lower than the average authentic 5&#x02032;ss (ME scores 7.55 &#x000b1; 1.81 versus 8.37 &#x000b1; 2.08, <italic>P</italic> = 0.0002) and also somewhat lower than the authentic counterparts of all unique cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in our dataset (7.55 &#x000b1; 1.81 versus 7.75 &#x000b1; 2.52), despite all having +5G and a higher than average relative frequency of +6T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Guanine at position +5 was proposed not to be obligatory for 5&#x02032;ss selection if the two preceding positions are purines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>); nevertheless 24/35 (69%) of unique authentic 5&#x02032;ss with point mutations of +5G had only purines at positions +3 and +4 and only a single authentic counterpart had pyrimidines at both positions.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows a comparison of the ME scores of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss by mutated position in the authentic and new 5&#x02032;ss consensus, respectively. Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss had similar ME values irrespective of the location of the point mutation (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05, F-test). In contrast, <italic>de novo</italic> sites created by mutations in a subset of intronic positions of the new 5&#x02032;ss consensus tended to be stronger, with statistically significant differences between <italic>de novo</italic> and cryptic 5&#x02032;ss for the highly conserved positions +1 and +2. In addition, we compared the ME scores of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss with their respective counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss induced by point mutations at positions +2 and +5 of natural sites were weaker than the authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activated by substitutions at position +1 (7.24 &#x000b1; 1.93 for position +2 and 7.22 &#x000b1; 2.06 for position +5 versus 8.34 &#x000b1; 2.21 for position +1, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01 for both comparisons). This is consistent with the notion that mutations at less conserved positions of authentic 5&#x02032;ss are less likely to completely inactivate the 5&#x02032;ss and result in recognizable phenotypes than mutations at position +1. The authentic counterparts of <italic>de novo</italic> sites induced by mutations at position +1 were significantly weaker than the authentic counterparts of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss induced by mutations at the same position (6.33 &#x000b1; 3.39 versus 8.34 &#x000b1; 2.21). The number of mutations for the remaining positions of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus was too small for meaningful comparisons. The average intrinsic strength of aberrant and authentic 5&#x02032;ss in each category is schematically summarized as the mean ME score in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>.
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Splice-site strength of authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss by position of the point mutation. The ME scores of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss induced by point mutations at positions -2 through +6 relative to the authentic and the new intron&#x02013;exon boundary, respectively, are followed by the ME scores of their authentic counterparts. Unlike the authentic counterparts, aberrant 5&#x02032;ss included pseudoexon sequences. Error bars represent standard deviations (except for a single value entry for authentic counterparts of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss generated by a mutation at position +5).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f5"/></fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Summary of the splice-site strength by category of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss. (<bold>A</bold>) cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in introns (upper panel) and exons (lower panel); (<bold>B</bold>) <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss in introns (upper panel) and exons (lower panel). The average ME scores are shown next to the corresponding category of 5&#x02032;ss. Exons are represented by boxes, introns are represented by lines. A cryptic exon is denoted by a black box. Canonical and aberrant RNA products are shown above and below the primary transcript, respectively. Mutations in the 9-nt consensus of authentic 5&#x02032;ss (A) or elsewhere (B) are schematically represented by stars.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkm402f6"/></fig></p><p>Taken together, cryptic 5&#x02032;ss generated <italic>in vivo</italic> were best predicted by models that accommodate nucleotide dependencies in the 5&#x02032;ss, particularly by the ME algorithm, which takes into account non-adjacent positions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). Discrimination of exonic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss from their authentic counterparts was more efficient than that for intronic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, because the former category of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss was weaker than the latter (<italic>P</italic> = 0.02), for which the NN model gave the best performance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>). Computational discrimination of <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss and their authentic counterparts was poor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B) as <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss were, on average, stronger than cryptic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>), particularly when generated by point mutations in highly conserved intronic positions of the new 5&#x02032;ss consensus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The intrinsic strength of exonic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss could not be distinguished from their authentic sites at all, pointing to the importance of exonic regulatory sequences in their selection. Finally, the authentic counterparts of aberrant (both cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic>) 5&#x02032;ss were weaker than a large collection of human 5&#x02032;ss, highlighting the practical importance of ranking splice sites in human disease genes using efficient computational tools. We propose that their systematic categorization may facilitate identification of intronic mutations or polymorphisms that affect pre-mRNA splicing, improve the interpretation of unknown alterations and, ultimately, increase the cost-effectiveness of mutation screening.</p></sec><sec><title>DBASS5</title><p>The DBASS5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dbass.org.uk/5">http://www.dbass.org.uk/5</ext-link>) provides access to the database of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss through the search option (Supplemental <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>A). DBASS5 can be searched by phenotype, gene, mutation, location of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss and their distance from authentic 5&#x02032;ss. If more than one database entry is found, the user can manually choose the details page (Supplemental <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>B), which shows nucleotide sequences flanking the authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss, the estimated strength of both authentic and aberrant 5&#x02032;ss and literature references with a PubMed hyperlink. DBASS5 visitors can register to obtain regular updates by email and can submit published data through a submission tool. Potential applications of DBASS5 include optimization of splice-site prediction algorithms, leading to improved prediction of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss, identification of genes and gene segments frequently involved in aberrant splice-site activation, detection of splicing mutations in a gene or phenotype of interest and selection of <italic>in vitro</italic> models for studying basic mechanisms of 5&#x02032;ss utilization.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec><title>The database of mutation-induced aberrant splice sites</title><p>This report presents the first comprehensive and publicly available database of aberrant splice sites in human disease genes. Together with a recently described database of aberrant 3&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), this combined resource now contains over 600 unique mutations that create or activate a total of 562 aberrant splice sites.</p><p>The overall number of reported aberrant 5&#x02032;ss was higher than aberrant 3&#x02032;ss, consistent with sequence limitations imposed by additional signal sequences upstream of 3&#x02032;ss (BPS and PPT) that are important for recognition of splice acceptor sites. The relative ratio of non-repetitive aberrant 5&#x02032;ss (<italic>n</italic> = 305) and 3&#x02032;ss (<italic>n</italic> = 257) [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>) and I.V.,&#x02009;(unpublished data)], was smaller than that reported for unique splicing mutations in the HGMD that were arbitrarily selected to reside in 5 exonic and 15 intronic nucleotides adjacent to natural splice sites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), i.e, 1.2 versus 1.5, respectively. The lower ratio might reflect a reporting bias towards mutations closer to authentic splice sites for exon skipping events. Mutations located upstream of intronic splicing signals that are required for 3&#x02032;ss selection could not be detected in many published mutation reports, because these regions were amplified only for a subset of introns or were not scanned at all. In addition, the lower ratio could be due to an under-representation of mutations leading to <italic>de novo</italic> splice sites in the HGMD as compared to our dataset. Also, the availability of suitable decoy splice sites near mutated sites is likely to determine if the outcome of a splicing mutation is exon skipping or aberrant splice-site activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>).</p><p>The higher number of cryptic than <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) can, probably to a large extent, be explained by a detection bias of DNA-based mutation screening, a method used to identify most aberrant 5&#x02032;ss in this dataset, towards coding regions and flanking intronic sequences. As explained above, classification of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss as cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss may occasionally be vague, but DBASS5 contains only two ambiguous examples (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>). Both cases were induced by G<sub>+1</sub>-to-T<sub>+1</sub> substitutions in 5&#x02032;ss that had G at position &#x02212;1, creating a new 5&#x02032;GT 1-nt upstream of the authentic 5&#x02032;'ss. Both cases were classified as cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in our analysis. The rarity of such cases confirms the validity of the previously proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>) categorization of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss.</p></sec><sec><title>Mutation pattern of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss</title><p>The most frequent point mutations that activated aberrant 5&#x02032;ss were purine transitions, accounting for 45.7% cases (11.1% A&#x0003e;G and 34.6% G&#x0003e;A mutations; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). This figure seems to be somewhat lower (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08) than the &#x0223c;54% (113/211) observed for aberrant 3&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>), probably due to a higher prevalence of transitions in the 3&#x02032;YAG than those in the 5&#x02032;ss consensus. Cryptic 5&#x02032;ss resulted from point mutations in each nucleotide of the 9-nt consensus except for position &#x02013;3, consistent with this position being the least conserved. However, position &#x02013;3 has previously been implicated in pathological exon skipping in well-documented cases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56 B57 B58 B59">56&#x02013;59</xref>), suggesting that &#x02013;3 substitutions in weak 5&#x02032;ss are also likely to result in aberrant 5&#x02032;ss, although these cases must be rare and aberrant splicing and putative phenotypic manifestations could be subtle.</p><p>As for positions adjacent to the 9-nt 5&#x02032;ss consensus, each of the reported single-base substitutions at intron positions +7 and +8 created new 5&#x02032;GT dinucleotides <italic>in situ</italic> that were used <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>). Despite position +7 exhibiting a predominance of purines after several rounds of functional 5&#x02032;ss selection experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), point mutations downstream of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus resulting in activation of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss have thus far not been reported. Among upstream substitutions in DBASS5, we found only a single case of an exonic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss generated by a C&#x0003e;T transition 11-nt upstream of an authentic 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>), consistent with a disruption of exonic splicing regulatory sequences.</p><p>Are point mutations at any position of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus sequence particularly prone to aberrant 5&#x02032;ss activation? As observed for mutations in the HGMD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>), position +1 led the frequency table in our dataset, with 49.8% and 39.4% mutations observed in the two studies, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). However, the overall distribution of mutations within the 5&#x02032;ss consensus was significantly different between the two. In particular, the proportion of mutations at position +5 was almost twice as high among cryptic 5&#x02032;ss than in the HGMD [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>)]. For unique point mutations leading to cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation, this position was in the second place and position +2 in the third, whereas this order was opposite for unique mutations in the HGMD (50 and 34 mutations versus 347 and 456, respectively; <italic>P</italic> = 0.004).</p><p>G at position +5 is nearly invariant in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>). In contrast, +5G is present in only &#x0223c;88% of <italic>S. pombae</italic> introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>) and &#x0223c;78% of human introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>), indicating that relief from the absolute requirement for G was an ancient evolutionary event. Comparison of exonized and non-exonized intronic Alu repeats revealed a higher number of +5Gs in exonized sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>). Mutations at position +5 have resulted in frequent activation of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss both in yeasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66 B67 B68 B69">66&#x02013;69</xref>) and humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, all references available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dbass.org.uk">http://www.dbass.org.uk</ext-link>). Our study is the first to provide statistical evidence that this position is important for distinct aberrant splicing outcomes. DBASS5 gives many examples of natural 5&#x02032;ss in which different point mutations resulted in the same cryptic 5&#x02032;ss. Similarly, there are numerous cases in the literature of identical exon skipping events caused by different point mutations in the same 5&#x02032;ss. The identification of several exceptions in humans using the DBASS5 and HGMD data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49 B50 B51 B52">49&#x02013;52</xref>) is consistent with an earlier observation in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, namely that cryptic 5&#x02032;ss activation by +5G&#x0003e;A mutation was not replicated for another 5&#x02032;ss point mutation in the same intron (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>). These rare examples may provide important insights into the requirements for activation of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss, as opposed to exon skipping events.</p><p>In addition to the local sequence context, the frequent occurrence of +5G&#x0003e;A substitutions underlying aberrant 5&#x02032;ss activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) can be explained by a more severe splicing outcome of these transitions. More dramatic splicing defects for +5G&#x0003e;A transitions than +5G transversions were found in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>). In contrast, each IVS1 + 5G&#x0003e;H mutation in the human proinsulin gene promoted activation of a competing decoy 5&#x02032;ss 26&#x02009;nt downstream of the authentic 5&#x02032;ss to the same extent, irrespective of the substituting nucleotide [(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>); J.K. and I.V., unpublished data], consistent with a position effect.</p><p>What interaction(s) at position +5 is crucial for aberrant 5&#x02032;ss activation? Authentic 5&#x02032;ss in which mutation at position +5 generated cryptic 5&#x02032;ss had a high proportion of +5G+6T (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Interestingly, the +5G+6T dinucleotide signifies the most frequent location for alternative 5&#x02032;ss across several species, and this preference was suggested to result from U1 binding rather than U6 binding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>). However, compensatory mutations in U1 snRNA that restore base-pairing with the mutated intron frequently fail to suppress aberrant splicing, suggesting that position +5 is engaged in additional interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71 B72 B73 B74">71&#x02013;74</xref>). Interaction of U6 snRNA with the 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>) at intron position +5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>) was partially suppressed by U6 mutations predicted to increase base-pairing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>). Although the 5&#x02032; ss has very limited complementarity to the U6 ACAGAG motif, this interaction seems to be important for accurate 5&#x02032;ss selection also in mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78 B79 B80">78&#x02013;80</xref>), albeit not in all systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>). In addition, cryptic splice sites have been induced by co-expression of splicing reporters with mutated snRNAs, including U1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>), U5 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>) and U6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77 B78 B79">77&#x02013;79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>), both in yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>) and mammals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>).</p><p>As U1 snRNP binds sequences that are not used as 5&#x02032;ss and is present in excess over U6, sequential occupancy by both snRNPs may be absolutely essential for accurate 5&#x02032;ss utilization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>). This would be consistent with rate-limiting U6 snRNA interactions with the pre-mRNA observed for U1-independent splicing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>) and loose requirements for U1 binding in numerous introns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>). Mutations of IVS+5G that resulted in cryptic 5&#x02032;ss occurred in relatively weak authentic 5&#x02032;ss and they are likely to further reduce U1 binding so that it may no longer be sufficient for accurate 5&#x02032;ss recognition. U6/U4.U5 snRNP would then bind to nearby pseudo-sites that are, on average, intrinsically stronger than the mutated authentic 5&#x02032;ss [<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref> and ref. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>)]. The strength of predicted base-pairing interactions at positions +5 and +6 in the authentic counterparts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) may hamper the transfer of these 5&#x02032;ss from U1 to U6. In fact, strong 5&#x02032;ss were reported to be inhibitory in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, potentially delaying the release of U1 and productive interactions with U6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>), although extended complementarity between U1 snRNA and a human immunodeficiency virus 1 donor site did not inhibit splicing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>). Mutations that destabilized a yeast 5&#x02032;ss/U6 duplex improved the second step of splicing and hyperstabilization of the 5&#x02032;ss/U6 interaction had the opposite effect, suggesting that changing the stability of these interactions alters the equilibrium between the first and second step conformations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>). Suppression of 5&#x02032;ss mutations by U6 in a hybrid reporter was more efficient when U1 could pair nearby than when pairing was restored further away (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>). In addition, position +5 may directly interact with U6 residues that base pair to the BPS recognition region of U2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>) as well as with other splicing factors, such as PRP8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>). Finally, sequential recognition of position +5 is likely to require contacts with exon-bound factors that may substitute for U1 interactions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>), and that may be essential for spliceosome assembly at authentic 5&#x02032;ss and contribute to the observed high number of cryptic sites as compared to <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>In summary, we have shown that cryptic 5&#x02032;ss in human disease genes are best predicted by computational methods that accommodate nucleotide dependencies and not by methods employing only nucleotide frequency matrices. Discrimination of intronic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss from their authentic counterparts was less effective than for exonic cryptic 5&#x02032;ss, as the former were intrinsically stronger than the latter. Computational prediction of exonic <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss was poor, suggesting that their activation <italic>in vivo</italic> critically depends on exonic splicing enhancers or silencers, rather than on the strength of the 5&#x02032;ss consensus, and that improved algorithms for their prediction will need to accommodate auxiliary splicing sequences. The authentic counterparts of both <italic>de novo</italic> and cryptic 5&#x02032;ss were weaker than the average human 5&#x02032;ss, highlighting the practical importance of ranking splice sites in disease genes to improve detection of splicing mutations. The mutation spectra of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 5&#x02032;ss were distinct and differed also from that underlying exon skipping events, implicating point mutations at position +5 in frequent activation of cryptic 5&#x02032;ss. Finally, the development of an online database of aberrant 5&#x02032;ss will facilitate detection of introns and exons frequently involved in aberrant splicing, identification of auxiliary sequences that control selection of aberrant splice sites, fine-tuning of splice-site prediction algorithms, identification of splicing mutations, as well as studies of the basic mechanisms of splice-site selection.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>[Supplementary Material]</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="nar_gkm402_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="nar_gkm402_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>This work was supported by the Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation International (1-2006-263), Telethon Onlus Foundation (GGP02453 and GGP06147), FIRB (RBNE01W9PM), and by the EC grant EURASNET-LSHG-CT-2005-518238. A.R.K. acknowledges support from NIH grant GM42699. We thank S. Mills, R. Sood, P. Gibbs and T. Bryant for technical help. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was shared equally by the above funding sources.</p><p><italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Krawczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Human Gene Mutation</source><year>1993</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>BIOS Scientific Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teraoka</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Telatar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker-Catania</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Onengut</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chessa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanal</surname><given-names>&#x000d6;.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Splicing defects in the ataxia-telangiectasia gene, <italic>ATM</italic>: underlying mutations and consequences</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1617</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ars</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazaro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Estivill</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations affecting mRNA splicing are the most common molecular defects in patients with neurofibromatosis type 1</article-title><source>Hum. Mol. Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krawczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hundrieser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mort</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hampe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single base-pair substitutions in exon-intron junctions of human genes: nature, distribution, and consequences for mRNA splicing</article-title><source>Hum. Mutat</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17001642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattox</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The regulation of splice-site selection, and its role in human disease</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9311728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nissim-Rafinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerem</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splicing regulation as a potential genetic modifier</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11858835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000e1;lovi&#x0010d;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaunt</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>INM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo&#x00159;echovsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variants in the human insulin gene that affect pre-mRNA splicing: is -23<italic>Hph</italic>I a functional single nucleotide polymorphism at IDDM2?</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>2006</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16380501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic variants in exons and introns: identifying the splicing spoilers</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15168696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of a novel database containing aberrant splicing mutations of mammalian genes</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>1994</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8163185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splicing in action: assessing disease causing sequence changes</article-title><source>J. Med. Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachidanandam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic differences between authentic and cryptic 5&#x02032; splice sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>6321</fpage><lpage>6333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000e1;lovi&#x0010d;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo&#x00159;echovsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biased exon/intron distribution of cryptic and <italic>de novo</italic> 3&#x02032; splice sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>4882</fpage><lpage>4898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16141195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cartegni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Listening to silence and understanding nonsense: exonic mutations that affect splicing</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source><year>2002</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11967553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictive identification of exonic splicing enhancers in human genes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1013</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12114529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Nostrand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General and specific functions of exonic splicing silencers in splicing control</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16797197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chasin</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational definition of sequence motifs governing constitutive exon splicing</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defective splicing, disease and therapy: searching for master checkpoints in exon definition</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3494</fpage><lpage>3510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roca</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachidanandam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of the inherent strength of human 5&#x02032; splice sites</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenchini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryptic splice site usage in exon 7 of the human fibrinogen B&#x003b2;-chain gene is regulated by a naturally silent SF2/ASF binding site within this exon</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16611940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of RNA secondary structure on the pre-mRNA splicing process</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>10505</fpage><lpage>10514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kornblihtt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promoter usage and alternative splicing</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Androphy</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulating role of RNA structure in alternative splicing of a critical exon in the spinal muscular atrophy genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17170000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buratti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Conti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Romano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baralle</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>hnRNP H binding at the 5&#x02032; splice site correlates with the pathological effect of two intronic mutations in the NF-1 and TSH&#x003b2; genes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4224</fpage><lpage>4236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15299088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Senapathy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA splice junctions of different classes of eukaryotes: sequence statistics and functional implications in gene expression</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1987</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>7155</fpage><lpage>7174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3658675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senapathy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splice junctions, branch point sites, and exons: sequence statistics, identification, and applications to genome project</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1990</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2314278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelbrecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of human mRNA donor and acceptor sites from the DNA sequence</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2067018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eeckman</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved splice site detection in Genie</article-title><source>J. Comput. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjems</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining a 5&#x02032; splice site by functional selection in the presence and absence of U1 snRNA 5&#x02032; end</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11911363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kammler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Konermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummheuer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hipp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Theiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel approach to describe a U1 snRNA binding site</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>6963</fpage><lpage>6975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14627829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vig</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ast</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis detects dependencies among the 5&#x02032; splice-site positions</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15100438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximum entropy modeling of short sequence motifs with applications to RNA splicing signals</article-title><source>J. Comput. Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15285897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanaraj</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Positional characterisation of false positives from computational prediction of human splice sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>744</fpage><lpage>754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10637326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busslinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moschonas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b2;<sup>+</sup> thalassemia: aberrant splicing results from a single point mutation in an intron</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1981</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6895866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felber</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abnormal RNA splicing causes one form of &#x003b1; thalassemia</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1982</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7151175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treisman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Proudfoot</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shander</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single-base change at a splice site in a &#x003b2;<sup>0</sup>-thalassemic gene causes abnormal RNA splicing</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1982</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7151176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vo&#x00159;echovsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aberrant 3&#x02032; splice sites in human disease genes: mutation pattern, nucleotide structure and comparison of computational tools that predict their utilization</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>4630</fpage><lpage>4641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Searls</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Computational methods in molecular biology</source><year>1998</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Science</publisher-name><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>164</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer methods to locate signals in nucleic acid sequences</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1984</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6364039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DINAMelt web server for nucleic acid melting prediction</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>W577</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krawczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neighboring-nucleotide effects on the rates of germ-line single-base-pair substitution in human genes</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>474</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9683596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deirdre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scadden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between the terminal bases of mammalian introns are retained in inosine-containing pre-mRNAs</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1995</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3236</fpage><lpage>3246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7621835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruis</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivens</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Siliciano</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction between the first and last intron nucleotides in the second step of pre-mRNA splicing is independent of other conserved intron nucleotides</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>5190</fpage><lpage>5195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7816605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5&#x02032; cleavage site in eukaryotic pre-mRNA splicing is determined by the overall 5&#x02032; splice region, not by the conserved 5&#x02032; GU</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1987</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3647844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seledtsov</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Solovyev</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SpliceDB: database of canonical and non-canonical mammalian splice sites</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02032;Driscoll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Perez</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeggo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodship</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A splicing mutation affecting expression of ataxia-telangiectasia and Rad3-related protein (ATR) results in Seckel syndrome</article-title><source>Nat. Genet</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12640452</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McConville</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stankovic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennox</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations associated with variant phenotypes in ataxia-telangiectasia</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8755918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kresse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tylki-Szymanska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mucopolysaccharidosis type II (Hunter syndrome): mutation &#x0201c;hot spots&#x0201d; in the iduronate-2-sulfatase gene</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1202</fpage><lpage>1209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8940265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuffery-Giraud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saquet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claustres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudoexon activation in the <italic>DMD</italic> gene as a novel mechanism for Becker muscular dystrophy</article-title><source>Hum. Mutat</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>608</fpage><lpage>614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12754707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wordsworth</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Handford</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marfan syndrome caused by a mutation in <italic>FBN1</italic> that gives rise to cryptic splicing and a 33 nucleotide insertion in the coding sequence</article-title><source>Hum. Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11702223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijbroek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Francomano</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bull</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyeritz</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fifteen novel <italic>FBN1</italic> mutations causing Marfan syndrome detected by heteroduplex analysis of genomic amplicons</article-title><source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7611299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Celebi</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacocke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of splicing defects in <italic>PTEN</italic> leading to exon skipping or partial intron retention in Cowden syndrome</article-title><source>Hum. Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruener</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Swisshelm</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sybert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genetic basis of Cowden&#x02032;s syndrome: three novel mutations in <italic>PTEN/MMACI/TEP1</italic></article-title><source>Hum. Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of complete gene structures in human genomic DNA</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9149143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attanasio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Moerloose</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonarakis</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Neerman-Arbez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of multiple cryptic donor splice sites by the common congenital afibrinogenemia mutation, <italic>FGA</italic> IVS4+1G&#x0003e;T</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2001</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1879</fpage><lpage>1881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Matejas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Luquetti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fraser and Ablepharon macrostomia phenotypes: Concurrence in one family and association with mutated <italic>FRAS1</italic></article-title><source>Am. J. Med. Genet. A</source><year>2006</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17163535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Poh-Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carriero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostasiewicz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Taketani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Piomelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel mutation in erythropoietic protoporphyria: an aberrant ferrochelatase mRNA caused by exon skipping during RNA splicing</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1993</year><volume>1181</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8481408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Langdown</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Baglin</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haemoglobin Dhofar is linked to the codon 29&#x02009;C&#x0003e;T (IVS-1&#x02009;nt-3) splice mutation which causes &#x003b2;<sup>+</sup> thalassaemia</article-title><source>Br. J. Haematol</source><year>1995</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7786794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A silent mutation induces exon skipping in the phenylalanine hydroxylase gene in phenylketonuria</article-title><source>Hum. Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11214902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aretz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlhaas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagenstecher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangold</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caspari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moslein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Propping</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Familial adenomatous polyposis: aberrant splicing due to missense or silent mutations in the <italic>APC</italic> gene</article-title><source>Hum. Mutat</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>370</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15459959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Bigas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabionet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Cid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Govea</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelante</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbones</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Estivill</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splice-site mutation in the <italic>PDS</italic> gene may result in intrafamilial variability for deafness in Pendred syndrome</article-title><source>Hum. Mutat</source><year>1999</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10571950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sidwell</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandison</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Seet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel mutation in the <italic>XPA</italic> gene associated with unusually mild clinical features in a patient who developed a spindle cell melanoma</article-title><source>Br. J. Dermatol</source><year>2006</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16792756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mugishima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okubo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel mutations of the <italic>FANCG</italic> gene causing alternative splicing in Japanese Fanconi anemia</article-title><source>J. Hum. Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spingola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grate</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ares</surname></name><name><surname>M.</surname><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide bioinformatic and molecular analysis of introns in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ast</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How did alternative splicing evolve?</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>773</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15510168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lev-Maor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Reznik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Belinky</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Graur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ast</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimal conditions for exonization of intronic sequences: 5&#x02032; splice site formation in Alu exons</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15099521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A point mutation in the conserved hexanucleotide at a yeast 5&#x02032; splice junction uncouples recognition, cleavage, and ligation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1985</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2986840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A quantitative analysis of the effects of 5&#x02032; junction and TACTAAC box mutants and mutant combinations on yeast mRNA splicing</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1985</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3935321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fouser</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in a yeast intron demonstrate the importance of specific conserved nucleotides for the two stages of nuclear mRNA splicing</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1986</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3513966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesser</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational analysis of pre-mRNA splicing in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> using a sensitive new reporter gene, <italic>CUP1</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1993</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8462846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox-Walsh</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertel</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic splice-site analysis reveals frequent alternative splicing close to the dominant splice site</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2047</fpage><lpage>2056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17053087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e9;raphin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretzner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A U1 snRNA:pre-mRNA base pairing interaction is required early in yeast spliceosome assembly but does not uniquely define the 5&#x02032; cleavage site</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1988</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2533</fpage><lpage>2538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3056718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siliciano</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>5&#x02032; splice site selection in yeast: genetic alterations in base-pairing with U1 reveal additional requirements</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1258</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3060402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>S&#x000e9;raphin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosbash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exon mutations uncouple 5&#x02032; splice site selection from U1 snRNA pairing</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>629</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2225068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of mammalian 5&#x02032; splice-site defects by U1 small nuclear RNAs from a distance</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>10470</fpage><lpage>10474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7937977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of U6 snRNA with the 5&#x02032;-splice site region of pre-mRNA in the spliceosome</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1310665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wassarman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of small nuclear RNA&#x02032;s with precursor messenger RNA during in vitro splicing</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1992</year><volume>257</volume><fpage>1918</fpage><lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1411506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandels-Lewis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seraphin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of U6 snRNA in 5&#x02032; splice site selection</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>2035</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8266100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crispino</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A U6 snRNA:pre-mRNA interaction can be rate-limiting for U1-independent splicing</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2314</fpage><lpage>2323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7557384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>U1 snRNA promotes the selection of nearby 5&#x02032; splice sites by U6 snRNA in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8595884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brackenridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Screaton</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient use of a &#x02018;dead-end&#x02019; GA 5&#x02032; splice site in the human fibroblast growth factor receptor genes</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>1631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Konermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertel</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extended base pair complementarity between U1 snRNA and the 5&#x02032; splice site does not inhibit splicing in higher eukaryotes, but rather increases 5&#x02032; splice site recognition</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>5112</fpage><lpage>5119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of a cryptic 5&#x02032; splice site by U1 snRNA</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11333015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in yeast U5 snRNA alter the specificity of 5&#x02032; splice-site cleavage</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2013092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sontheimer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seiwert</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in the conserved loop of human U5 snRNA generate the use of novel cryptic 5&#x02032; splice sites in vivo</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1993</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>5191</fpage><lpage>5200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8262062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesser</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in U6 snRNA that alter splice site specificity: implications for the active site</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>262</volume><fpage>1982</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8266093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eperon</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ireland</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathways for selection of 5&#x02032; splice sites by U1 snRNPs and SF2/ASF</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1993</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3607</fpage><lpage>3617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maroney</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Romfo</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional recognition of 5&#x02032; splice site by U4/U6.U5 tri-snRNP defines a novel ATP-dependent step in early spliceosome assembly</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10983979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konarska</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilardell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Query</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repositioning of the reaction intermediate within the catalytic centre of the spliceosome</article-title><source>Mol. Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16483935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valadkhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A tertiary interaction detected in a human U2-U6 snRNA complex assembled in vitro resembles a genetically proven interaction in yeast</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allele-specific genetic interactions between Prp8 and RNA active site residues suggest a function for Prp8 at the catalytic core of the spliceosome</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1970</fpage><lpage>1982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10444595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Beggs</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of U6 snRNA-protein interactions</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>1999</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1470</fpage><lpage>1481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10580475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crispino</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Blencowe</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementation by SR proteins of pre-mRNA splicing reactions depleted of U1 snRNP</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>1866</fpage><lpage>1869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8091213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarn</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SR proteins can compensate for the loss of U1 snRNP functions in vitro</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2704</fpage><lpage>2717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7958927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krawczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single base-pair substitutions in pathology and evolution: two sides to the same coin</article-title><source>Hum. Mutat</source><year>1996</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8807332</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>