<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plbi</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17914903</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1994992</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0050264</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">06-PLBI-RA-0861R3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="sici">plbi-05-10-13</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subject>Genetics and Genomics</subject><subject>Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Segregation of Odor Identity and Intensity during Odor Discrimination in <italic>Drosophila</italic> Mushroom Body</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Segregation of Odor Identity and Intensity</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Shouzhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, New York, United States of America</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>Barry</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austria</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>tully@cshl.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>5</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e264</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement> &#x000a9; 2007 Xia and Tully.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Molecular and cellular studies have begun to unravel a neurobiological basis of olfactory processing, which appears conserved among vertebrate and invertebrate species. Studies have shown clearly that experience-dependent coding of odor identity occurs in &#x0201c;associative&#x0201d; olfactory centers (the piriform cortex in mammals and the mushroom body [MB] in insects). What remains unclear, however, is whether associative centers also mediate innate (spontaneous) odor discrimination and how ongoing experience modifies odor discrimination. Here we show in na&#x000ef;ve flies that G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-mediated signaling in MB modulates spontaneous discrimination of odor identity but not odor intensity (concentration). In contrast, experience-dependent modification (conditioning) of both odor identity and intensity occurs in MB exclusively via G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated signaling. Our data suggest that spontaneous responses to odor identity and odor intensity discrimination are segregated at the MB level, and neural activity from MB further modulates olfactory processing by experience-independent G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent encoding of odor identity and by experience-induced G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-dependent encoding of odor intensity and identity.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><sec id="st1"><title/><p>Considerable progress has been made in understanding how olfaction works as the receptor proteins, sensory neurons, and brain circuitry responsible have become increasingly well-characterized. However, olfactory processing in higher brain centers, where neuronal activity is assembled into the perception of odor quality, is poorly understood. Here, we have addressed how the mushroom body (MB)&#x02014;a secondary olfactory center&#x02014;is involved in olfactory discrimination. We manipulated the MB by ablation, disruption of synaptic transmission, and interruption of key cellular signaling molecules in na&#x000ef;ve flies and in flies trained to discriminate odors. We first show that although both odor identity and intensity are encoded in the MB, only the former requires G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent signaling and is necessary for na&#x000ef;ve flies to spontaneously discriminate different odors. We then show that training flies to alter their olfactory response requires G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated signaling in MB for both odor intensity and odor identity. We have thus identified (i) segregation of odor identity and odor intensity at the MB level in na&#x000ef;ve flies and (ii) different G-protein-dependent signaling pathways for spontaneous versus experience-dependent olfactory discrimination.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Experience-dependent modification of odor identity and intensity occurs in the mushroom body (MB) of flies exclusively via G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated signaling. In contrast, G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-mediated signaling in MB modulates spontaneous discrimination of odor identity but not odor intensity.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>citation</meta-name><meta-value>Xia S, Tully T (2007) Segregation of odor identity and intensity during odor discrimination in <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom body. PLoS Biol 5(10): e264. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0050264">10.1371/journal.pbio.0050264</ext-link></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Naturally, most odors are experienced as complex mixtures in the environment. Consequently, an animal's ability to discriminate between two odor cues reflects the interplay between spontaneous and experience-dependent processes [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Odor discrimination traditionally has been assessed either by using conditioning procedures to reveal that an animal can learn a conditioned response for one odor over another and therefore can discriminate them (e.g., [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]) or by demonstrating experience-dependent olfactory adaptation (e.g., [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]). When trying to identify the underlying cellular and molecular mechanisms for odor discrimination and associative learning, however, this approach becomes confounding. The cAMP signaling pathway, for instance, has been shown to be involved in both olfactory processing and associative learning in mammals and in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Similarly, experience-dependent changes in odor discrimination have been shown to occur in the piriform cortex of vertebrates [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and in the mushroom body (MB) of <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], both of which are activated by odor stimulation in na&#x000ef;ve animals [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>Odors elicit a variety of behavioral responses in <italic>Drosophila</italic> via a relatively simple but sensitive olfactory system readily accessible to genetics [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. A number of behavioral assays have been reported for screening single-gene mutations that cause defects in olfactory function and in olfactory associative learning. The predominant learning assay employs Pavlovian conditioned discrimination between two odors [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. A behavioral mutant might display an abnormal behavioral response in this assay because of (i) a sensorimotor deficit to odor(s), (ii) a sensorimotor deficit to footshock, (iii) a sensorimotor deficit to odor discrimination, or (iv) a deficit in the association of odor and footshock. Traditionally, sensorimotor deficits to odors and to footshock have been assessed in a T-maze using an olfactory acuity assay ([<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]; also see below) and a shock reactivity assay [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. For the former, flies are given a choice between an odor and air. For the latter, flies are given a choice between footshock versus no footshock. To date, mutants are considered to be associative learning/memory mutants if they behave normally in these two sensorimotor assays. Significantly, no assay for sensorimotor deficits in odor discrimination per se has yet been developed.</p><p>Ultimately to address this issue, we have developed two novel assays to measure discrimination of odor intensity and odor identity with a T-maze [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] in na&#x000ef;ve flies. Work on odor intensity discrimination in na&#x000ef;ve flies then prompted us to develop a third novel assay to measure conditioned discrimination of odor intensity (cf. [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]). Importantly, genetic manipulations in <italic>Drosophila</italic> can be used to link these behavioral responses to specific molecular mechanisms. By disrupting MB function in four distinct ways (i.e., developmental lesion of MB, silencing of synaptic transmission from MB, RNA interference [RNAi]&#x02013;mediated suppression of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-mediated signaling, and disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated signaling in MB) and assessing the effects with each of our four distinct behavioral assays, we have asked whether a secondary olfactory center (MB) is required for spontaneous odor discrimination and whether the same cAMP and IP<sub>3</sub> signaling pathways that are known to mediate odor transduction in peripheral sensory neurons [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] also regulate olfactory processing in the central nervous system. Our results demonstrate that (i) MB is required for spontaneous discrimination of odor identity but not odor intensity via a G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent signaling pathway and (ii) MB is required for conditioned discrimination of odor identity or odor intensity via a G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-dependent signaling pathway.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>To explore how <italic>Drosophila</italic> MB participates in spontaneous versus conditioned odor discrimination, we designed three novel odor discrimination assays&#x02014;a spontaneous odor intensity assay, a spontaneous odor identity assay, and a conditioned odor intensity assay (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sd001">Protocol S1</xref> for details)&#x02014;to use along with our original conditioned odor identity assay [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. With these four behavioral protocols, we were able to quantify (i) discrimination of odor intensity in na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>A), (ii) discrimination of odor identity in na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figures S1</xref>B, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg003">S3</xref>), (iii) discrimination of odor intensity in conditioned flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>C), and (iv) discrimination of odor identity in conditioned flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>D).</p><p>We then disrupted MB structure or function in four distinct ways and assessed their effects with each of these four behavioral assays. First, we lesioned MB using chemical ablation [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. When hydroxyurea feeding is restricted to the first few hours after hatching, this method kills proliferating cells during development and results in a dramatic reduction of adult MB and loss of a portion of the antennal lobes (ALs; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg004">Figure S4</xref>). Second, we acutely blocked dynamin-dependent synaptic transmission from MB of transgenic flies by using three different PGAL4 enhancer-trap drivers to express UAS-<italic>shi<sup>ts1</sup></italic> (shi<sup>ts</sup>) preferentially in MB [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Third, we disrupted expression of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of transgenic flies by using the same PGAL4 drivers to express a UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> (RNAi) construct [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. We then duplicated the essential experiment with a second RNAi (UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>) transgene [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Both UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> and UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> produced severe knockdowns of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> expression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg005">Figure S5</xref>; see also [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). Fourth, we disrupted G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> signaling in MB of transgenic flies by using the same PGAL4 drivers to express UAS-<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>Q215L</sup> (<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*), a constitutively active stimulatory subunit of guanosine triphosphate-binding protein [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. As a genetic control, wild-type <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> transgene (UAS-<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>) was overexpressed using the same PGAL4 drivers.</p><sec id="s2a"><title>Spontaneous Odor Intensity Discrimination Does Not Require the Normal Function of MB</title><p>MB ablation had no effect on flies' spontaneous odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figure 1</xref>A) and avoidance of individual odors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st001">Table S1</xref>). To check whether neuronal activity from MB is acutely involved with the spontaneous odor response, synaptic transmission from MB was transiently silenced by driving transgenic expression of shi<sup>ts</sup> with several MB-specific PGAL4 drivers. C309 and 247 drive transgenic expression in all lobes of MB, while 201Y drives transgenic expression preferentially in &#x003b3;-lobes ([<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg004">Figure S4</xref>). Consistent with MB ablation, transient silencing of synaptic transmission from MB left spontaneous odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figure 1</xref>B) and avoidance of individual odors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st001">Table S1</xref>) unchanged. Similarly, neither disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> by overexpression of UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> nor disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> by overexpression of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>*</italic> with the same PGAL4 drivers interfered with flies' spontaneous odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figure 1</xref>C and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">1</xref>D) or avoidance of individual odors (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st001">Table S1</xref>). These observations indicate that MB is not required for discrimination of odor intensity or perception of individual odors in na&#x000ef;ve flies. Such olfactory processing perhaps is accomplished in ALs or other brain regions, such as the lateral horn [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><fig id="pbio-0050264-g001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Spontaneous Odor Intensity Discrimination Does Not Require the Normal Function of MB</title><p>In this and the following figures, all control groups are shown in black bars, and the experimental groups in white bars, or blue when statistically significantly different from the control (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), and all experiments were done in a balanced and experimenter-blind manner.</p><p>Spontaneous intensity discrimination between different concentrations of MCH (left panels) or BA (right panels) was not affected (A) by MB ablation (+HU), (B) by transient block (30 &#x000b0;C) of temperature-sensitive (20 &#x000b0;C, permissive; 30 &#x000b0;C, restrictive) <italic>shibire</italic>-dependent synaptic transmission using three different MB PGAL4 drivers (C309, 247, and 201Y), (C) by RNAi-mediated disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> using the same MB PGAL4 drivers, or (D) by overexpression of constitutively active <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* (with <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup> as controls) using two MB PGAL4 drivers (C309 and 247). <italic>n =</italic> 4 PIs for all groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0050264.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Spontaneous Odor Identity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> Signaling</title><p>MB ablation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>A) and transient silencing of synaptic transmission from MB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>B) disrupted flies' spontaneous odor identity discrimination, suggesting that MB is acutely involved with the process. Some spontaneous response remained, in particular after MB ablation, suggesting other brain regions may also be involved in the discrimination of odor identity. This is consistent with the fact that projection neurons do not form synaptic collaterals with the calyx of MB after hydroxyurea-based ablation, whereas their arborizations in the lateral horn remain [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p><fig id="pbio-0050264-g002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Spontaneous Odor Identity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> Signaling</title><p>(A&#x02212;E) Spontaneous odor identity discrimination between MCH and BA was severely disrupted (A) by MB ablation (+HU), (B) by transient block (30 &#x000b0;C) of synaptic transmission from MB in C309/shi<sup>ts</sup>, 247/shi<sup>ts</sup>, or 201Y/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies, (C) by developmental disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/C309, ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/247, and ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/201Y flies, (D) by adult-specific, physiological disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>, GAL80<sup>ts</sup>/C309 flies at restrictive (30 &#x000b0;C for 3 d) but not permissive (18 &#x000b0;C for 3 d) temperature, or (E) by developmental disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of <italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>/C309 or <italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>/247 flies.</p><p>(F&#x02212;H) Spontaneous odor identity discrimination was not affected (F) when the <italic>drl</italic> gene was knocked down in MB via RNAi-mediated disruption (T. T., H. Tang, and M. Regulski, unpublished data) in <italic>drl</italic>
<sup>RNAi</sup>/C309 or <italic>drl</italic>
<sup>RNAi</sup>/247 flies, (G) when <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> was disrupted in MB of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/C309, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/247, or <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/201Y flies, or (H) in <italic>rut</italic> and <italic>dnc</italic> mutants. <italic>n =</italic> 4 PIs for all groups.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0050264.g002"/></fig><p>RNAi-mediated disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB with the same PGAL4 drivers was sufficient to interfere with spontaneous odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>C). To rule out the possibility that a developmental defect underlay this adult defect in the spontaneous odor identity response, the <italic>tub</italic>-GAL80<sup>ts</sup> transgene was used along with the binary PGAL4/UAS system [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Groups of flies, raised at 18 &#x000b0;C, were kept for 3 d either at 18 &#x000b0;C (permissive for inhibition of PGAL4 by GAL80<sup>ts</sup>) or 30 &#x000b0;C (restrictive for GAL80<sup>ts</sup> function) before testing of spontaneous odor identity discrimination. The performance was significantly disrupted in transgenic C309/+; ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>, GAL80<sup>ts</sup>/+ flies at the restrictive but not at the permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>D), suggesting an adult-specific physiological role for <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> during spontaneous odor identity discrimination. To rule out the possibility of an off-target RNAi effect (cf. [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]), a second RNAi transgene construct, UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], was evaluated. Again, we saw significant disruption of spontaneous odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>E). As a further control for a more general &#x0201c;poisoning&#x0201d; of neuronal function by RNAi, we showed that expression of a UAS-<italic>drl</italic>
<sup>RNAi</sup> transgene in MB had no effect on this odor response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>F). Collectively, these results demonstrate, to our knowledge for the first time, an adult-specific role in the central nervous system for G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> signaling during discrimination of odor identity in na&#x000ef;ve flies.</p><p>In contrast to the effect of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>,</italic> disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> signaling in MB had no effect on spontaneous odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>G). Consistent with this observation, the <italic>rutabaga</italic> and <italic>dunce</italic> mutants, in which two other components of the cAMP signaling pathway (i.e., adenylyl cyclase and cAMP-specific phosphodiesterase, respectively) are defective [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], showed normal spontaneous odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>H). Taken together, these observations suggest that (i) odor identity discrimination in na&#x000ef;ve flies occurs independently of the cAMP signaling pathway and (ii) G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent signaling in MB specifically contributes to this response.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Conditioned Odor Intensity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> Signaling</title><p>MB ablation completely abolished conditioned odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">Figure 3</xref>A), suggesting that conditioned odor intensity discrimination requires an intact MB. Similarly, transient block of synaptic transmission from MB severely disrupted conditioned odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">Figure 3</xref>B), suggesting an acute role for neuronal activity in MB for this conditioned response. Finally, disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> but not G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> signaling also severely disrupted conditioned odor intensity discrimination, and the effect was adult-specific and physiological (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">Figure 3</xref>C&#x02013;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">3</xref>E). Considering that spontaneous odor intensity discrimination occurs independent of MB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figure 1</xref>), these observations reveal that (i) there is an &#x0201c;anatomical dissection&#x0201d; for odor intensity discrimination between na&#x000ef;ve and conditioned flies and (ii) G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated neural plasticity in MB modulates odor intensity discrimination in conditioned but not in na&#x000ef;ve flies.</p><fig id="pbio-0050264-g003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Conditioned Odor Intensity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> Signaling</title><p>Conditioned odor intensity discrimination between different concentrations of MCH (left panels) or BA (right panels) was (A) abolished by MB ablation (+HU), (B) disrupted by transient block (30 &#x000b0;C) of synaptic transmission from MB in C309/shi<sup>ts</sup>, 247/shi<sup>ts</sup>, or 201Y/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies, (C) not affected by disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/C309, ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/247, or ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/201Y flies, (D) severely affected by developmental disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> in MB of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/C309 or <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/247 flies, and (E) abolished in an adult-specific manner by disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> (at restrictive temperature, 30 &#x000b0;C, for 3 d) in MB of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*, GAL80<sup>ts</sup>/C309 flies. <italic>n =</italic> 6 PIs for each group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0050264.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Conditioned Odor Identity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> Signaling</title><p>MB ablation abolished conditioned odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>A), confirming a previous report [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Conditioned odor identity discrimination with a different odor pair, 3-octanol and 4-methyl-cyclohexanol (MCH), has been reported to be abolished by transient silencing of synaptic transmission from MB in C309/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and mildly disrupted even at the permissive temperature in 247/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Here, we confirmed and extended such observations by showing that conditioned odor identity discrimination between MCH and benzaldehyde (BA) was severely disrupted by transient silencing of synaptic transmission from MB in C309/shi<sup>ts</sup> and 247/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies and mildly disrupted in 201Y/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies at restrictive temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>B).</p><fig id="pbio-0050264-g004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Conditioned Odor Identity Discrimination Requires Synaptic Transmission from MB and Depends on G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> Signaling</title><p>Conditioned odor identity discrimination between MCH and BA was (A) abolished by MB ablation (+HU), (B) disrupted by transient block (30 &#x000b0;C) of synaptic transmission from MB in C309/shi<sup>ts</sup>, 247/shi<sup>ts</sup>, or 201Y/shi<sup>ts</sup> flies, (C) mildly affected by disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB of ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/C309, ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/247, or ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/201Y flies, (D) severely diminished by developmental disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> in MB of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/C309, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/247, or <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/201Y flies, (E) abolished by adult-specific, physiological disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> in MB of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*, GAL80<sup>ts</sup>/C309 flies at restrictive (30 &#x000b0;C) but not permissive (18 &#x000b0;C) temperature, and (F) disrupted in <italic>rut</italic> or <italic>dnc</italic> mutants. <italic>n =</italic> 6 PIs for each group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0050264.g004"/></fig><p>Disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB had only a very mild effect on conditioned odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>C). Considering that the same flies were defective for spontaneous odor identity discrimination, this mild effect may be indirect.</p><p>Conditioned odor identity discrimination between 3-octanol and MCH has been reported to be disrupted when <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* but not <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup> is overexpressed in MB [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Here we again confirmed our previous finding with 3-octanol and MCH (data not shown) and extended it by showing a similar effect with a different odor pair, MCH and BA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>D). Again, to rule out the possibility that a developmental defect underlay this effect on conditioned odor identity discrimination, the <italic>tub</italic>-GAL80<sup>ts</sup> transgene was used to restrict expression of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* in adults. Conditioned odor identity discrimination was abolished in transgenic C309/+; <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*, GAL80<sup>ts</sup>/+ flies when kept at the restrictive but not at the permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>E), suggesting an adult-specific physiological role for G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> during conditioned odor identity discrimination. Consistent with this notion, <italic>rutabaga</italic> and <italic>dunce</italic> mutants showed disrupted conditioned odor identity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">Figure 4</xref>F), as demonstrated long ago [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. These results are strikingly different from those for spontaneous odor identity discrimination, revealing a &#x0201c;genetic dissection&#x0201d; for odor identity discrimination between na&#x000ef;ve and conditioned flies. In MB, G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> signaling mediates odor identity discrimination in na&#x000ef;ve flies, while G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> signaling mediates odor identity discrimination in conditioned flies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The use of a Pavlovian conditioned odor discrimination assay [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] over the past 20 y has helped to establish the view that G-protein-mediated cAMP signaling in MB subserves this form of associative learning [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Now, by developing additional behavioral measures, we are able to dissect odor discrimination into four functionally distinct components: the spontaneous response to odor intensity, the spontaneous response to odor identity, the conditioned response to odor intensity, and the conditioned response to odor identity. Our results refine our view of olfactory behavior as it relates to MB function, revealing an anatomical and molecular (genetic) dissection between odor identity and odor intensity in this higher brain center (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0050264-t001">Table 1</xref>). We have established MB as one important anatomical site for odor identity discrimination in na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Odor intensity discrimination, in contrast, does not require MB at all in na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Within MB, different G-protein-mediated signaling pathways distinguish odor identity discrimination between na&#x000ef;ve and conditioned flies. G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent signaling regulates spontaneous responses to odor identity, while G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-dependent signaling is involved in conditioned responses to odor identity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">4</xref>). Strikingly, disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-dependent signaling produces similar effects on conditioned responses to both odor identity and odor intensity, while disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> has little or no effect on these behavioral responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g004">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pbio-0050264-t001" content-type="1col" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of Four Experimental Manipulations of MB Function on Four Behavioral Assays of Odor Discrimination</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0050264.t001"/></table-wrap><sec id="s3a"><title>Segregation of Odor Identity and Odor Intensity in Na&#x000ef;ve Flies</title><p>Odor discrimination is usually assayed in the context of olfactory adaptation (perceptual learning) or conditioning (associative learning) because of the difficulty in directly evaluating the process in na&#x000ef;ve animals (e.g., [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]). Our spontaneous odor identity discrimination assay, where na&#x000ef;ve flies are allowed to recognize and discriminate a second odor from a saturated odor as the background (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figures S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg003">S3</xref>), is analogous to a saturation discrimination paradigm in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans,</italic> the only other known discrimination assay developed for na&#x000ef;ve animals [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. When an odor is saturated in intensity, higher concentrations produce no further change in response (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">Figure S2</xref>A and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">S2</xref>C). Against a saturated background odor, a &#x0201c;foreground&#x0201d; odor may be represented in two possible ways. First, the odor may activate additional receptors in the sensory neurons, leading to activation of additional subsets of glomeruli and the corresponding MB neurons (cf. [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]). Second, the foreground odor may activate additional neural processes or signaling pathways, leading to activation of additional subsets of MB neurons. Either way, flies clearly recognize the presence of the foreground odor and discriminate it from a background odor (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">Figure S2</xref>C). More importantly, our saturation assay appears to quantify odor identity discrimination independent of odor intensity discrimination in na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">Figure S2</xref>C).</p><p>MB cells respond differently to different odors, and some of them are reported to be concentration-invariant [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], but their behavioral function in odor identity and intensity discrimination is unknown. It also remains unclear whether the piriform cortex encodes odor identity in vertebrates [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Hydroxyurea-induced ablation or shi<sup>ts</sup>-dependent silencing of MB severely diminishes (but does not abolish) spontaneous odor identity discrimination but not odor intensity discrimination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g001">Figures 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g002">2</xref>; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0050264-t001">Table 1</xref>), suggesting that MB specifically contributes to behavioral responses to odor identity in na&#x000ef;ve flies. The effect for our particular odor pair is partial, suggesting that processing of odor identity (but not intensity) may be of major importance for na&#x000ef;ve flies, and thus needs to recruit more than one perceptual center (i.e., MB). This notion leads to the conclusion that odor identity and odor intensity are distinct and must be processed, at least in part, through different neuronal circuitries in the central brain. Our demonstration that MB mediates spontaneous responses to odor identity is particularly important for understanding olfactory processing in central olfactory centers, where neuronal activity may be recruited to generate the perception of odor identity (cf. [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]).</p><p>Nonetheless, increases in odor concentration recruit additional glomeruli at ALs and lead to changes in the firing patterns of projection neurons, similar to those caused by changes in odor identity [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Consequently, the spatiotemporal codes for odor identity and intensity may be confounded in ALs. Such observations highlight our hypothesis that MB serves to segregate representations of odor identity and odor intensity. Such an anatomical segregation between odor identity and intensity in a higher brain center like MB is consistent with the observations that (i) odor identity and intensity assays engage different (although overlapping) central brain regions in human [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and (ii) odor identity and structure are coded separately within the piriform cortex [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Therefore, olfactory information in <italic>Drosophila</italic> may be decomposed into various features and processed in distinct central perceptual centers (also see [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]), as in other sensory systems [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Segregation of Odor Identity and Odor Intensity in Na&#x000ef;ve versus Conditioned Flies</title><p>Little is known about G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>- or G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-mediated signaling pathways in secondary olfactory centers in spite of the facts that (i) G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> appears to be involved in olfactory signal transduction in sensory neurons [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], (ii) G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> is involved in conditioned odor identity discrimination in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and (iii) these higher centers clearly are involved in experience-dependent modification of odor discrimination in vertebrates [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and in <italic>Drosophila</italic> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The fact that MB is required (i) for spontaneous responses to odor identity but not intensity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0050264-t001">Table 1</xref>) and (ii) for conditioned responses to odor identity [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] prompted us to check G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>- versus G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-mediated signaling pathways in MB.</p><p>Disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB affects the spontaneous response to odor identity but unexpectedly affects the conditioned response to odor identity only minimally. Disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> in MB, on the other hand, affects the conditioned response to odor identity but does not affect the spontaneous response to odor identity (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0050264-t001">Table 1</xref>). Such (i) exclusion of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> from the conditioned response to odor identity and of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> from the spontaneous response to odor identity and (ii) specificity of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> for the spontaneous response to odor identity and of G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> for the conditioned response to odor identity constitute a dual dissection of spontaneous and conditioned odor identity discrimination. Moreover, the conditioned response to odor intensity is abolished by disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> in MB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0050264-g003">Figure 3</xref>D), while the spontaneous response to odor intensity occurs independent of MB, suggesting different anatomical contributions to spontaneous and conditioned odor intensity discrimination. Such an anatomical/molecular dissection of spontaneous and conditioned odor responses suggests that the learned response occurs independently of the spontaneous response, questioning the traditional experiments where odor discrimination per se is evaluated in the context of olfactory learning.</p><p>Finally, the correspondence between the conditioned responses to odor intensity and odor identity when disrupted by MB ablation, MB silencing, or jamming of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> is simply striking (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pbio-0050264-t001">Table 1</xref>). This general observation argues that, in contrast to the fact that the spontaneous responses to odor intensity or odor identity are segregated at the MB level, G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated neuronal plasticity in MB nonetheless underlies behavioral changes to both.</p><p>Our data collectively demonstrate that (i) odor identity encoded in MB contributes to olfactory discrimination through a G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>-dependent signaling process, whereas odor intensity encoded in MB exists but is not necessary for behavioral responses in na&#x000ef;ve flies and (ii) G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>-mediated signaling in MB is exclusively involved in neural plasticity, which then modulates behavioral responses to both odor intensity and identity. Such segregation of odor identity and odor intensity at the MB level in na&#x000ef;ve flies and identification of different G-protein-dependent signaling pathways for spontaneous and conditioned odor discrimination, combined with function imaging [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and the recently established spatial map of olfactory representations in MB [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], make it possible to check how neuronal activity in MB is assembled into the perception of odor identity (cf. [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Fly stocks.</title><p>Fly stocks included wild-type Canton-S <italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic> (CS10); the PGAL4 insertions 247 [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], C309, and 201Y; and UAS constructs UAS-<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], shi<sup>ts</sup> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>-RNAi [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. UAS-<italic>GFP</italic>
<sup>S65T</sup> was obtained from the Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flystocks.bio.indiana.edu/">http://flystocks.bio.indiana.edu/</ext-link>). All stocks were &#x0201c;Cantonized&#x0201d; by outcrossing the heterozygous virgins to <italic>w<sup>1118</sup></italic> (CS10) males for six generations, selecting for the mini-white<sup>+</sup> eye color associated with each P element transposant.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Odorants.</title><p>The following odors were used: two alcohols, 3-octanol and MCH; one aromatic compound, BA; one ester, ethyl acetate; one ketone, diacetyl; one amine, triethylamine; and thiazole. Some chemically similar odors were also tested including (R)-(&#x02212;)-carvone and (S)-(+)-carvone, (R)-(&#x02212;)-octanol and (S)-(+)-octanol, pentanol, 2-hexanol, and hexanol. All odors were dissolved in heavy mineral oil (Fisher Scientific, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fishersci.com/">https://www.fishersci.com/</ext-link>) and delivered to the training chamber or the two T-maze arms with a &#x0201c;test bubbler&#x0201d; [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p><p>For conditioned discrimination, the concentration of MCH was chosen as 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> (in mineral oil [v/v]) [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] or alternatively 1.0 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>. Then the relative concentrations of BA (0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> or 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>) were determined so that na&#x000ef;ve flies distributed themselves 50:50 in the T-maze when given a choice between MCH and BA. For odor avoidance, MCH and BA were tested at concentrations from 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> to 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. For saturation discrimination, the concentrations were much higher and varied with odors as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st002">Table S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Behavioral assays.</title><p>To assess the flies' ability to sense individual odors, &#x0201c;fresh&#x0201d; air was delivered in one T-maze arm and odor (MCH or BA at different concentrations; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st001">Table S1</xref>) was delivered in the other, with all other parameters identical to those used during the traditional Pavlovian conditioned discrimination assay ([<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]; and see below). Groups of about 100 na&#x000ef;ve flies were lowered to the center of the T-maze, and their odor avoidance was quantified [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p><p>To assay spontaneous intensity discrimination, groups of about 100 na&#x000ef;ve flies were given a choice in the T-maze between higher (i.e., 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) and lower (i.e., 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>) concentrations of the same odor (either MCH or BA). Two groups of flies were always tested in one complete run to produce a pure measure of spontaneous intensity discrimination for na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>A). The first group was given the higher concentration in the left T-maze arm. A second, reciprocal group of na&#x000ef;ve flies then was given the higher odor concentration in the right T-maze arm.</p><p>To assay spontaneous identity discrimination, groups of na&#x000ef;ve flies were given a choice between a saturated background odor and a mixture containing the same background and a second odor. Crucially, the second odor was always weaker than or equivalent to the saturated background in intensity, and the background odor was &#x0201c;saturated&#x0201d; for intensity, thereby eliminating intensity differences from this assay (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sd001">Protocol S1</xref> for details). Again, two groups of flies were always tested in one complete run to produce a pure measure of spontaneous identity discrimination for na&#x000ef;ve flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>B). The first group of na&#x000ef;ve flies was exposed to a saturating concentration of the background odor (MCH<sup>S</sup>) plus an &#x0201c;equivalent&#x0201d; concentration of a second odor (BA<sup>E</sup>) in the left T-maze arm and the background (MCH<sup>S</sup>) only in the right T-maze arm. For the reciprocal group of na&#x000ef;ve flies, the saturated background (MCH<sup>S</sup>) alone was presented in the left T-maze arm, and the mixture of the background and the second odor (MCH<sup>S</sup> + BA<sup>E</sup>) presented in the right arm.</p><p>To assay conditioned intensity discrimination, groups of flies were first subjected to associative conditioning with different concentrations of the same odors before being tested for their acquired response to the different intensities. Again, two groups of flies were always tested in one complete run to produce a pure measure of acquired intensity discrimination for conditioned flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>C). The first group of about 100 flies was first exposed to the higher odor concentration (10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> of either MCH or BA; CS+) and subjected to footshock (US) for 60 s and then (after 45 s of air alone) exposed to the lower concentration (10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> of either BA or MCH; CS&#x02212;) without foot shock for another 60 s. A second reciprocal group of flies was trained with the lower odor concentration as the CS+ and the higher odor concentration as the CS&#x02212;.</p><p>We also assayed conditioned identity discrimination, which corresponds to the traditional conditioned discrimination assay of Tully and Quinn [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] with minor modifications [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Again, two groups of flies were always tested in one complete run to produce a pure measure of acquired identity discrimination for conditioned flies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg001">Figure S1</xref>D). The first group of about 100 flies was exposed sequentially to the CS+ (MCH) paired with footshock (US) and to the CS&#x02212; (BA) without footshock. A second reciprocal group of flies was trained with BA as the CS+ and MCH as the CS&#x02212;.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Statistics.</title><p>Due to the nature of their mathematical derivation, performance indices (PIs) are distributed normally. Hence, the data were evaluated via one- or two-way ANOVAs. Subsequent pairwise planned comparisons were adjusted for experiment-wise error (&#x003b1;&#x02032;), keeping the overall &#x003b1; equal to 0.05. All data are presented as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Disruptions of MB structure or function.</title><p>MB ablation was achieved by feeding newly hatched larvae with hydroxyurea for about 6 h [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As a control, newly hatched larvae were fed with yeast suspension for 6 h.</p><p>Silencing of MB was achieved with the shi<sup>ts</sup> transgene, which reversibly interferes with neuronal transmission in a temperature-dependent, dominant-negative fashion when overexpressed in a wild-type background [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. shi<sup>ts</sup> was crossed with C309 (C309/shi<sup>ts</sup>), 247 (247/shi<sup>ts</sup>), and 201Y (201Y/shi<sup>ts</sup>) males and grown at 18 &#x000b0;C throughout development. As a genetic control, shi<sup>ts</sup> transgenic flies also were crossed to wild-type flies (+/shi<sup>ts</sup>). For the spontaneous intensity and identity assays, na&#x000ef;ve flies were tested at 20 &#x000b0;C (permissive) as controls, or shifted to 30 &#x000b0;C (restrictive) for 30 min to block neural activity from MB before testing. For the conditioned intensity and identity assays, the flies were trained and tested immediately after training at 20 &#x000b0;C as controls, or shifted to 30 &#x000b0;C for 30 min to acutely block the synaptic transmission from MB before training and testing.</p><p>Disruption of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> was achieved by blocking the transcription of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> in MB by combining a UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>-RNAi construct with the above MB-PGAL4 drivers in transgenic flies (ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/C309, ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/247, and ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/201Y). For genetic controls, ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/+, +/C309, +/247, and +/201Y flies were generated. As a confirmation, transcription of <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> was also blocked in MB by combining an independent RNAi transgene, UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>, with C309 and 247 in transgenic flies (<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>/C309 and <italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>/247).</p><p>To disrupt <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub>,</italic> a constitutively activated stimulatory heterotrimeric guanosine triphosphate-binding protein, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*, was overexpressed to &#x0201c;jam&#x0201d; G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> signaling in MB by crossing <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* flies with the above PGAL4 drivers (<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/C309, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/247, and <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/201Y). As genetic controls, a wild-type <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic> transgene was overexpressed using the same PGAL4 drivers (<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>/C309, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>/247, and <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>/201Y). Further control genotypes included <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>*/+, <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup>/+, +/C309, +/247, and +/201Y.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Measure of the vapor concentration.</title><p>The total molecules of each odor or odor mixture were measured in a paired manner for the four different behavioral tests of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-sg002">Figure S2</xref>C with a PID detector (miniPID-2, Aurora Scientific, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aurorascientific.com/">http://www.aurorascientific.com/</ext-link>). The measurement was repeated six times and averaged to produce the actual vapor concentration for each odor or odor mixture.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>Western blotting.</title><p>For Western blotting, the adult head was homogenized with lysis buffer and centrifuged at 14,000 rpm at 4 &#x000b0;C for 50 min, and then the supernatant was saved. Lysate proteins were electrophoresed on a 12% SDS-PAGE, then electroblotted onto PVDF membranes. Immobilized proteins were probed with rabbit polyclonal anti-Gq (1:500 dilution) antiserum (SC-392; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scbt.com/">http://www.scbt.com/</ext-link>), or rabbit polyclonal anti-actin (1:5,000 dilution) antibody (A5060; Sigma-Aldrich, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/">http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/</ext-link>) as the loading control, and the membrane was incubated with HRP-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG secondary antibody (1:5,000 dilution). The positive signal was visualized with the ECL System (GE Healthcare, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gehealthcare.com/">http://www.gehealthcare.com/</ext-link>). Quantification of Western blot results was performed by digital image analysis using an Epson (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epson.com/">http://www.epson.com/</ext-link>) scanner and ImageJ (National Institute of Mental Health, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nimh.nih.gov/">http://www.nimh.nih.gov/</ext-link>); experiments were repeated six times for +/Elav, UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/Elav, and UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup>/Elav flies. The level of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> was normalized to the actin control.</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Whole-mount GFP expression.</title><p>The protocol for whole-mount GFP expression was described before [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Briefly, homozygous PGAL4 females were crossed to homozygous UAS-<italic>GFP</italic>
<sup>S65T</sup> males. Three- to five-day-old heterozygous female progeny were examined for GFP expression patterns. The whole brains were carefully transferred to 4% paraformaldehyde for 30 min, then to 4% paraformaldehyde + 0.25% Triton X-100 (Fisher Scientific) for 30 min under mild vacuum. Brains were then soaked in FocusClear (CelExplorer Labs, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.celexplorer.com/">http://www.celexplorer.com/</ext-link>) solution for 5 min and mounted in a drop of the same solution [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The whole-mount brains were imaged with a Zeiss (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zeiss.com/">http://www.zeiss.com/</ext-link>) LSM 510 confocal microscope, and stacks of confocal images were taken through the full thickness of the central brain. The distance between successive images (<italic>z</italic>-axis distance) was adjusted for the refractive index mismatch of the air and mounting medium as described previously [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In some cases, frontal and dorsal projections were rendered with Amira 3.1 (Mercury Computer Systems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tgs.com/">http://www.tgs.com/</ext-link>) after removing optical slices between the brain surface and MBs to better reveal internal structures.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sg001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title>The Behavioral Protocols for Different Odor Discrimination Assays</title><p>To control for potential side bias in the T-maze, two reciprocal groups always were tested as one complete experiment. A PI for the complete experiment was defined as the average of the PIs (always calculated as the number of flies avoiding the measured variable [i.e., the high concentration for spontaneous odor intensity discrimination, the mixture of the saturated background and the foreground odor for spontaneous odor identity discrimination, or the CS+ concentration or odor for conditioned odor intensity and odor identity discrimination assays] minus that avoiding the other &#x0201c;control&#x0201d; variable [i.e., the low concentration, the saturated background alone, or the CS&#x02212; concentration or odor in the relevant assays], divided by the total number of flies and finally multiplied by 100) from the two reciprocal groups.</p><p>(A) The spontaneous odor intensity discrimination assay for na&#x000ef;ve flies. Na&#x000ef;ve flies were allowed to choose between two different concentrations (C1 and C2) of the same odors (10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> and 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for MCH, or 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> and 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for BA), with the higher concentration delivered to the left arm in one group and to the right arm in the reciprocal group.</p><p>(B) The spontaneous odor identity discrimination assay for na&#x000ef;ve flies. Na&#x000ef;ve flies were allowed to make a choice between a saturated background odor (e.g., MCH) and a mixture consisting of the same saturated odor and a second foreground odor (e.g., BA). The mixture was delivered to the left arm in one group and to the right arm in the reciprocal group to produce a pure measure of spontaneous odor identity discrimination.</p><p>(C) The conditioned odor intensity discrimination assay for trained flies. The flies were conditioned to avoid one of the two concentrations (C1 or C2) of the same odors (10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> and 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for MCH, or 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> and 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for BA), with US (marked with red electric volt symbol) associated with the higher concentration in one group and the lower concentration in the reciprocal group. The higher concentration was always delivered to the left arm during testing to cancel out both spontaneous odor intensity response and side bias.</p><p>(D) The conditioned odor identity discrimination assay for trained flies. The flies were conditioned to avoid one of the two equivalent odors (i.e., both spontaneous identity and intensity responses are close to zero; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for MCH and 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> for BA), with US associated with MCH in one group and with BA in the reciprocal group. MCH was always delivered to the left arm for both reciprocal groups.</p><p>(681 KB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sg001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sg002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title>The Saturation Discrimination Assay for Measuring Spontaneous Odor Identity Discrimination in Na&#x000ef;ve Flies</title><p>(A) Saturation of the background odor. To saturate MCH as the background odor, na&#x000ef;ve flies were allowed to choose in the T-maze between 2 &#x000d7; [MCH] versus 1 &#x000d7; [MCH]. As the concentration of MCH was increased, a threshold (i.e., about 10%) was reached at which flies would fail to recognize the intensity difference, thereby yielding a PI of zero. At that concentration, MCH was considered saturated for intensity.</p><p>(B) Determination of the equivalent intensity of the foreground odor. To determine the concentration of BA equivalent to that of the saturated MCH (MCH<sup>S</sup>; i.e., 15% throughout the study), na&#x000ef;ve flies were given a choice between [BA] and MCH<sup>S</sup>. As the concentration of BA was increased, the distributions of flies in the T-maze approached 50:50, yielding a PI of zero. That concentration of BA, BA<sup>E</sup> (about 1.5%), was considered equivalent to saturated MCH.</p><p>(C) The saturation discrimination assay was produced by presenting either MCH<sup>S</sup> + BA<sup>E</sup> versus MCH<sup>S</sup> (black bar, chosen as our standard assay throughout the study) or MCH<sup>S</sup> + BA<sup>E</sup> versus 2 &#x000d7; MCH<sup>S</sup> (grey bar) in the T-maze. Because MCH<sup>S</sup> (15%) was saturated, flies produced a score close to zero when presented with 2 &#x000d7; MCH<sup>S</sup> versus MCH<sup>S</sup> (<italic>p =</italic> 0.18). Similarly, because BA<sup>E</sup> (1.5%) was equivalent to MCH<sup>S</sup>, flies also produced a score close to zero when presented with BA<sup>E</sup> versus MCH<sup>S</sup> (<italic>p =</italic> 0.46). The non-zero scores (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001) for the two discrimination groups indicate that na&#x000ef;ve flies are able to recognize the presence of BA and discriminate it from the saturated background of MCH. Scores from these two discrimination assays were not different from each other (<italic>p =</italic> 0.79), further confirming that MCH was saturated for intensity. The actual vapor concentrations of the individual odors or the mixture of MCH<sup>S</sup> + BA were quantified and are shown in the lower panel.</p><p>(D) Saturation discrimination is concentration-dependent. Na&#x000ef;ve flies were allowed to discriminate [BA] from the MCH<sup>S</sup> (15%) across a wide range of concentrations (0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>, 0.4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, 0.75 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and 0.15 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Odor discrimination improved as [BA] increased.</p><p>(E) Saturation discrimination is influenced by exposure time to odors. Na&#x000ef;ve flies were given a discrimination assay testing MCH<sup>S</sup> + BA<sup>E</sup> versus MCH<sup>S</sup> for different lengths of time (30, 45, 60, 90, and 120 s). Optimal scores were produced quickly (i.e., with 30 s). When the time was longer than 60 s, discrimination scores dropped substantially.</p><p>
<italic>n =</italic> 4 PIs for each group.</p><p>(572 KB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sg002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sg003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title>Spontaneous Discrimination between Chemically Different Odors</title><p>(A) Na&#x000ef;ve flies were tested for their ability to discriminate 3-octanol, BA, ethyl acetate, diacetyl, triethylamine, and thiazole from MCH<sup>S</sup> (15%; grey columns); or MCH, 3-octanol, ethyl acetate, diacetyl, thiethylamine, and thiazole from BA<sup>S</sup> (10%; black columns) as the saturated background odor (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio-0050264-st001">Table S1</xref> for concentrations of all odors).</p><p>(B) Reciprocally, na&#x000ef;ve flies were tested for their ability to discriminate MCH<sup>E</sup> (grey columns) and BA<sup>E</sup> (black columns) from saturated 3-octanol, ethyl acetate, diacetyl, and thiazole as the background.</p><p>
<italic>n</italic> = 4 PIs for each group.</p><p>(406 KB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sg003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sg004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><title>Confirmation of Lesion of MB</title><p>To confirm the hydroxyurea-induced ablation of MB, we expressed UAS-<italic>GFP</italic>
<sup>S65T</sup> in MB (and a few other regions) using 201Y (201Y/UAS-<italic>GFP</italic>) PGAL4 drivers, or in projection neurons from ALs to MB using GH146 (GH146/UAS-<italic>GFP</italic>) PGAL4 drivers. Ten flies were sampled for the 201Y/UAS-<italic>GFP</italic> genotype with or without hydroxyurea treatment, and five flies were sampled for GH146/UAS-<italic>GFP</italic> with or without the treatment. In all cases, MB was ablated after hydroxyurea treatment, as indicated by the absence of UAS-<italic>GFP</italic> signal in MB calyces, consistent with previous reports [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].</p><p>(A) Without hydroxyurea treatment (&#x02212;HU), UAS-<italic>GFP</italic> was expressed strongly in MB and a few scattered big neurons, and weakly in ALs with 201Y.</p><p>(B) Without hydroxyurea treatment (&#x02212;HU), UAS-<italic>GFP</italic> was targeted to ALs and the projection neurons with GH146. Some weak GFP signal was also present in MB.</p><p>(C) The 201Y-driven GFP signal was reduced in MB specifically by hydroxyurea treatment (+HU), but still was present in the scattered neurons and ALs, suggesting the specific ablation of MB. The residual GFP signal in MB might represent the embryonic Kenyon cell fibers, unaffected by the treatment [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p><p>(D) The GH146-driven GFP signal was completely removed in MB by hydroxyurea (+HU). The hydroxyurea treatment also reduced GFP expression in ALs and the projection neurons, resulting from ablation of one lateral neuroblast [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].</p><p>(3.4 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sg004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sg005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><title>Knockdown of the G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> Protein</title><p>There was a 50-bp overlap between the sequences used for creating UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> [<xref rid="pbio-0050264-b037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] transgenes. Therefore, Western blot analyses were done to confirm the RNAi-mediated disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> protein with these two RNAi transgenes. Wild-type, UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>, or UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> males were crossed with the Elav-PGAL4 virgins. Adult heads from their progenies were used for Western blot analyses. The quantification of six repetitions is shown in lower panel. G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> expression was greatly disrupted in flies carrying both Elav-PGAL4 and UAS-ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> (dsG<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub>/Elav) or UAS-<italic>dG<sub>q</sub></italic>
<sup>1F1</sup> (dG<sub>q</sub>
<sup>1F1</sup>/Elav) as compared with that in control flies carrying only Elav-PGAL4 driver.</p><p>(4.1 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sg005.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-sd001"><label>Protocol S1</label><caption><title>Detailed Description of Saturation Discrimination Assay in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and Supporting References</title><p>(76 KB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.sd001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-st001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><title>Olfactory Acuity to MCH and BA after Chemical Lesion of MB, Silencing of MB with shi<sup>ts</sup>, or Disruption of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> or G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> Signaling in MB</title><p>Chemical ablation of MB with hydroxyurea treatment (+HU), silencing of MB, or disruptions of G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub> or G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub> do not affect olfactory acuity. No significant differences were detected between MB-ablated (+HU) and control (&#x02212;HU) flies (<italic>p</italic> &#x02265; 0.29), between +/shi<sup>ts</sup> control flies and those with synaptic transmission from MB blocked (<italic>p &#x02265;</italic> 0.21), between ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic>/+ control flies and those with ds<italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;q</sub></italic> expressed in MB (<italic>p &#x02265;</italic> 0.39), or among genotypes overexpressing <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>
<sup>+</sup> or <italic>G<sub>&#x003b1;s</sub></italic>* (<italic>p &#x02265;</italic> 0.23).</p><p>(60 KB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.st001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pbio-0050264-st002"><label>Table S2</label><caption><title>Chemical Odors and Their Concentrations Used in the Saturation Discrimination Assay</title><p>(51 KB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pbio.0050264.st002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Drs. Savitha Kalidas, Dean P. Smith, Santanu Banerjee, Gaiti Hasan, and the Bloomington <italic>Drosophila</italic> Stock Center for fly stocks and reagents. We thank Drs. Zachary Mainen and Matthew Smear for the PID meter, and Dr. Matthew Smear and Mr. Joshua Sanders for technique support. We thank Drs. Santanu Banerjee and Gaiti Hasan for sharing unpublished observations. We also thank Drs. Martin Heisenberg, Josh Dubnau, Ann-Shyn Chiang, Yi Zhong, and Akira Mamiya for helpful discussions and comments.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="ack1" fn-type="con"><p>
<bold>Author contributions.</bold> SX conceived, designed, and performed the experiments. SX and TT analyzed the data and wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn id="ack2" fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>
<bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by grants to TT from the National Institutes of Health and Dart Neurosciences.</p></fn><fn id="ack3" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing interests.</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AL</term><def><p>antennal lobe</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BA</term><def><p>benzaldehyde</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>G</italic><sub>&#x003b1;<italic>s</italic></sub>*</term><def><p>UAS-<italic>G</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;<italic>s</italic></sub>
<sup>Q215L</sup>
</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MB</term><def><p>mushroom body</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCH</term><def><p>4-methyl-cyclohexanol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>performance index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RNAi</term><def><p>RNA interference</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>shi<sup>ts</sup></term><def><p>UAS-<italic>shi<sup>ts1</sup></italic>
</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pbio-0050264-b001"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The fundamental role of memory in olfactory perception</article-title>
<source>Trends Neurosci</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>243</fpage>
<lpage>247</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12744840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b002"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ache</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Olfaction: Diverse species, conserved principles</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>417</fpage>
<lpage>430</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16269360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b003"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Outline of a theory of olfactory processing and its relevance to humans</article-title>
<source>Chem Senses</source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>i3</fpage>
<lpage>5</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15738168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b004"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Spontaneous versus reinforced olfactory discriminations</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>6842</fpage>
<lpage>6845</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b005"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimshek</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bus</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihaljevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Enhanced odor discrimination and impaired olfactory memory by spatially controlled switch of AMPA receptors</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<elocation-id>e354.</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16216087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b006"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L'Etoile</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Olfaction and odor discrimination are mediated by the <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> guanylyl cyclase <italic>ODR-1</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>575</fpage>
<lpage>586</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10774726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b007"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelliher</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziesmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Munger</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zufall</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Importance of the CNGA4 channel gene for odor discrimination and adaptation in behaving mice</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>4299</fpage>
<lpage>4304</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b008"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadohisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Olfactory cortical adaptation facilitates detection of odors against background</article-title>
<source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>1888</fpage>
<lpage>1896</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b009"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devaud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Acebes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Odor exposure causes central adaptation and morphological changes in selected olfactory glomeruli in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>6274</fpage>
<lpage>6282</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b010"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of olfactory discrimination: Converging evidence for common principles across phyla</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>595</fpage>
<lpage>631</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9056726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b011"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronnett</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>G proteins and olfactory signal transduction</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Physiol</source>
<volume>64</volume>
<fpage>189</fpage>
<lpage>222</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b012"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Genetic approaches to memory storage</article-title>
<source>Trends Genet</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>463</fpage>
<lpage>470</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10529810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b013"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Gene discovery in <italic>Drosophila</italic>: New insights for learning and memory</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>407</fpage>
<lpage>444</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9530502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b014"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez-Diaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcorta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The cAMP transduction cascade mediates olfactory reception in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Behav Genet</source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<lpage>406</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15082937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b015"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gottfried</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Dissociable codes of odor quality and odorant structure in human piriform cortex</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>467</fpage>
<lpage>479</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16446149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b016"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulyas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Olfactory functions are mediated by parallel and hierarchical processing</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>735</fpage>
<lpage>745</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10896168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b017"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasselmo</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Acetylcholine and associative memory in the piriform cortex</article-title>
<source>Mol Neurobiol</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>
<lpage>29</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b018"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Barkai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A molecular mechanism for stabilization of learning-induced synaptic modifications</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>192</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14741100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b019"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Associative learning disrupted by impaired Gs signaling in <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom bodies</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>274</volume>
<fpage>2104</fpage>
<lpage>2107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b020"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Belle</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Associative odor learning in <italic>Drosophila</italic> abolished by chemical ablation of mushroom bodies</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>263</volume>
<fpage>692</fpage>
<lpage>695</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8303280</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b021"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The role of <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom body signaling in olfactory memory</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>293</volume>
<fpage>1330</fpage>
<lpage>1333</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11397912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b022"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Disruption of neurotransmission in <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom body blocks retrieval but not acquisition of memory</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>411</volume>
<fpage>476</fpage>
<lpage>480</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11373680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b023"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pologruto</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Stereotyped odor-evoked activity in the mushroom body of <italic>Drosophila</italic> revealed by green fluorescent protein-based Ca<sup>2+</sup> imaging</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>6507</fpage>
<lpage>6514</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15269261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b024"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Genetic manipulation of the odor-evoked distributed neural activity in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom body</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>267</fpage>
<lpage>276</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11182097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b025"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Combinatorial effects of odorant mixes in olfactory cortex</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>311</volume>
<fpage>1477</fpage>
<lpage>1481</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16527983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b026"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Odor maps in the olfactory cortex</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<fpage>7724</fpage>
<lpage>7729</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b027"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Illig</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haberly</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Odor-evoked activity is spatially distributed in piriform cortex</article-title>
<source>J Comp Neurol</source>
<volume>457</volume>
<fpage>361</fpage>
<lpage>373</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12561076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b028"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stopfer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Intensity versus identity coding in an olfactory system</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>991</fpage>
<lpage>1004</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12971898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b029"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Olfaction in <italic>Drosophila:</italic> From odor to behavior</article-title>
<source>Trends Genet</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>180</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8984732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b030"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>Classical conditioning and retention in normal and mutant <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>
<volume>157</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>
<lpage>277</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b031"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boynton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>
<italic>latheo,</italic> a new gene involved in associative learning and memory in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster,</italic> identified from P element mutagenesis</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>131</volume>
<fpage>655</fpage>
<lpage>672</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1321066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b032"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dura</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Preat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Identification of <italic>linotte,</italic> a new gene affecting learning and memory in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>J Neurogenet</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8295074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b033"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Computation of olfactory signals in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>
<volume>152</volume>
<fpage>373</fpage>
<lpage>383</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b034"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1977</year>
<article-title>Properties of learning and memory in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>J Comp Physiol [A]</source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>69</fpage>
<lpage>89</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b035"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Conditional modification of behavior in <italic>Drosophila</italic> by targeted expression of a temperature-sensitive shibire allele in defined neurons</article-title>
<source>J Neurobiol</source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>92</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b036"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalidas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Novel genomic cDNA hybrids produce effective RNA interference in adult <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>177</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11804566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b037"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkiteswaran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Srikanth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Compensation of inositol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor function by altering sarco-endoplasmic reticulum calcium ATPase activity in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> flight circuit</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>8278</fpage>
<lpage>8288</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16899722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b038"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zars</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Localization of a short-term memory in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>288</volume>
<fpage>672</fpage>
<lpage>675</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10784450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b039"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heimbeck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugnon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>A central neural circuit for experience-independent olfactory and courtship behavior in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>15336</fpage>
<lpage>15341</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11742061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b040"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Heimbeck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gendre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>de Belle</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Neuroblast ablation in <italic>Drosophila</italic> P[GAL4] lines reveals origins of olfactory interneurons</article-title>
<source>J Neurobiol</source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>443</fpage>
<lpage>456</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9110257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b041"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Evidence of off-target effects associated with long dsRNAs in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content> cell-based assays</article-title>
<source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>833</fpage>
<lpage>838</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16964256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b042"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Creanga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lum</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Beachy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Prevalence of off-target effects in <italic>Drosophila</italic> RNA interference screens</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>443</volume>
<fpage>359</fpage>
<lpage>363</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16964239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b043"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Denome</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Molecular analysis of cDNA clones and the corresponding genomic coding sequences of the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila dunce</named-content>
<sup>+</sup> gene, the structural gene for cAMP phosphodiesterase</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>83</volume>
<fpage>9313</fpage>
<lpage>9317</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3025834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b044"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> learning and memory gene rutabaga encodes a Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Calmodulin-responsive adenylyl cyclase</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>479</fpage>
<lpage>489</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1739965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b045"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Deconstructing memory in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>R700</fpage>
<lpage>R713</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b046"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartwieg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvitz</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Odorant-selective genes and neurons mediate olfaction in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>515</fpage>
<lpage>527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8348618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b047"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A map of olfactory representation in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom body</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>128</volume>
<fpage>1205</fpage>
<lpage>1217</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17382887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b048"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Comparative chemosensation from receptors to ecology</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>444</volume>
<fpage>295</fpage>
<lpage>301</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b049"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Axel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Two-photon calcium imaging reveals an odor-evoked map of activity in the fly brain</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>112</volume>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>282</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12553914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b050"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Blockade of neurotransmission in <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom bodies impairs odor attraction, but not repulsion</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1900</fpage>
<lpage>1904</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14588247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b051"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Segregation of form, color, movement, and depth: Anatomy, physiology, and perception</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>240</volume>
<fpage>740</fpage>
<lpage>749</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3283936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b052"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shipp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>The functional logic of cortical connections</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>335</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>317</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3047584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b053"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiner</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutter</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Modular organization of frequency integration in primary auditory cortex</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>501</fpage>
<lpage>529</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b054"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Preat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boynton</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Vecchio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Genetic dissection of consolidated memory in <italic>Drosophila</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>47</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7923375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b055"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Three-dimensional mapping of brain neuropils in the cockroach, <named-content content-type="genus-species">Diploptera punctata</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>J Comp Neurol</source>
<volume>440</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11745603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b056"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Correale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Mushroom body ablation impairs short-term memory and long-term memory of courtship conditioning in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>967</fpage>
<lpage>977</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10624959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b057"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hotta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Proliferation pattern of postembryonic neuroblasts in the brain of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>149</volume>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>148</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1728583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pbio-0050264-b058"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Spatial and temporal patterns of neurogenesis in the central nervous system of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Drosophila melanogaster</named-content>
</article-title>
<source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>145</fpage>
<lpage>157</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3119399</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>