<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Comput Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Comput. Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plcb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">ploscomp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Computational Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-734X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7358</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18463699</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2265480</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLCB-RA-0253R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subject>Developmental Biology/Developmental Molecular Mechanisms</subject><subject>Neuroscience/Behavioral Neuroscience</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification of Synaptic Targets of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pumilio</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Pum Translational Targets</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Gengxin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wanhe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Qing-Shuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Regulski</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>Nishi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barditch</surname><given-names>Jody</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>Adrian R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Michael Q.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>Josh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Cold Spring Harbor, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Graduate Program in Molecular and Cellular Biology, State University of New York Stony Brook, Stony Brook, New York, United States of America</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Bussemaker</surname><given-names>Harmen</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Columbia University, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>mzhang@cshl.edu</email> (MZ); <email>dubnau@cshl.edu</email> (JD)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GC WL QZ TT AK MZ JD. Performed the experiments: GC WL QZ NS. Analyzed the data: GC WL QZ NS JD. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: GC WL QZ MR JB TT AK MZ JD. Wrote the paper: GC WL QZ JD.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>2</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e1000026</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Chen et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> Pumilio (Pum) protein is a translational regulator involved in embryonic patterning and germline development. Recent findings demonstrate that Pum also plays an important role in the nervous system, both at the neuromuscular junction (NMJ) and in long-term memory formation. In neurons, Pum appears to play a role in homeostatic control of excitability via down regulation of <italic>para</italic>, a voltage gated sodium channel, and may more generally modulate local protein synthesis in neurons via translational repression of <italic>eIF-4E</italic>. Aside from these, the biologically relevant targets of Pum in the nervous system remain largely unknown. We hypothesized that Pum might play a role in regulating the local translation underlying synapse-specific modifications during memory formation. To identify relevant translational targets, we used an informatics approach to predict Pum targets among mRNAs whose products have synaptic localization. We then used both in vitro binding and two in vivo assays to functionally confirm the fidelity of this informatics screening method. We find that Pum strongly and specifically binds to RNA sequences in the 3&#x02032;UTR of four of the predicted target genes, demonstrating the validity of our method. We then demonstrate that one of these predicted target sequences, in the 3&#x02032;UTR of <italic>discs large (dlg1)</italic>, the <italic>Drosophila</italic> PSD95 ortholog, can functionally substitute for a canonical NRE (Nanos response element) in vivo in a heterologous functional assay. Finally, we show that the endogenous <italic>dlg1</italic> mRNA can be regulated by Pumilio in a neuronal context, the adult mushroom bodies (MB), which is an anatomical site of memory storage.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author Summary</title><p>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pumilio (Pum) protein was originally identified as a translational control factor for embryo patterning. Subsequent studies have identified Pum's role in multiple biological processes, including the maintenance of germline stem cell, the proliferation and migration of primordial germ cells, olfactory leaning and memory, and synaptic plasticity. Pum is highly conserved across phyla, i.e., from worm to human; however, the mRNA targets of Pum within each tissue and organism are largely unknown. On the other hand, the prediction of RNA binding sites remains a hard question in the computational field. We were interested in finding Pum targets in the nervous system using fruit flies as a model organism. To accomplish this, we used the few Pum binding sequences that had previously been shown in vivo as &#x0201c;training sequences&#x0201d; to construct bioinformatic models of the Pum binding site. We then predicted a few Pum mRNA targets among the genes known to function in neuronal synapses. We then used a combination of &#x0201c;golden standards&#x0201d; to verify these predictions: a biochemical assay called gel shifts, and in vivo functional assays both in embryo and neurons. With these approaches, we successfully confirmed one of the targets as Dlg, which is the <italic>Drosophila</italic> ortholog of human PSD95. Therefore, we present a complete story from computational study to real biological functions.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>
<italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> Pumilio (Pum) protein is one of the founding members of the PUF RNA-binding protein family. Its function in the posterior body patterning of <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos is relatively well studied. Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> first identified two copies of sequence elements located in the 3&#x02032; untranslated region (3&#x02032;UTR) of maternal <italic>hunchback</italic> (<italic>hb</italic>) mRNA, named Nanos Response Elements (NREs), which are essential for normal abdominal segmentation. It was later shown that Pum binds these elements, recruits Nanos (Nos) and Brain Tumor (Brat), and represses the translation of maternal <italic>hb</italic> mRNA <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Pum was also reported to temporally regulate the translation of <italic>Drosophila bicoid</italic> (<italic>bcd</italic>) mRNA, which plays a key role in anterior development <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gamberi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. In addition, Pum, acting together with Nos, is required for germline development in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos, and <italic>Cyclin B</italic> (<italic>CycB</italic>) mRNA appears to be a target of translational repression by this complex <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-AsaokaTaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. As a characteristic of the PUF family proteins, the minimal RNA-binding domain of Pum comprises eight imperfect repeats, is evolutionarily conserved across species from yeast to human <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and, therefore, is termed the PUF domain or Pumilio Homology Domain (Pum-HD). This RNA-binding domain appears to be sufficient for the function of Pum in vivo during <italic>Drosophila</italic> abdominal segmentation <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><p>More recently, Pum has been found to play a role in the nervous system at the neuromuscular junction <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Schweers1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, in voltage-gated Na<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> current homeostasis in the CNS <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Mee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> and in long-term memory <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Dubnau et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> employed the complementary &#x0201c;genomics&#x0201d; approaches of (i) a large-scale behavioral screen for mutants defective in one-day memory, and (ii) DNA microarray screening to identify genes in normal flies that are transcriptionally regulated during long-term memory formation. <italic>pum</italic> was found with both approaches: it is transcriptionally upregulated during memory formation after spaced training (which results in long-term memory) relative to massed training (which results only in shorter forms of memory), and two independent transposon insertions into <italic>pum</italic> yielded mutants with defective one-day memory after spaced training. In addition to <italic>pum</italic>, six other components of a pathway putatively involved in local translational control were identified: <italic>staufen</italic>, <italic>orb</italic> (CPEB), <italic>moesin</italic> and <italic>eIF-2G</italic> were transcriptionally regulated during memory formation, whereas transposon-mediated lesions were found in or near <italic>oskar</italic> (<italic>norka</italic> mutant) and <italic>eIF-5C</italic> (<italic>krasavietz</italic> mutant).</p><p>Local mRNA translation within dendrites of neurons has been proposed to be a mechanism for activity-dependent synaptic plasticity (reviewed in <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Steward1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>). We hypothesized that Pum might play a role in local translation involved in synapse-specific modifications during memory formation <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Consistent with this notion, Ye et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Ye1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> showed that Pum and Nos act together and play a critical role in the morphogenesis of high-order dendritic branches in <italic>Drosophila</italic> peripheral neurons, and that Nos colocalizes with RNA granules in dendrites. The role of Pum-dependent regulation in neurons also may be conserved <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Vessey1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p><p>Despite these genetic observations of Pum/Nos function in neurons, only a few neuronal targets of Pum have been demonstrated in vivo <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Mee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. A large number of Pum-associated mRNAs have been recently identified from oocytes and early embryos <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. These include a number of neuronally expressed genes whose in vivo relationship with Pum remains to be shown. As a complementary approach to screen for potentially relevant neuronal (and in particular synaptic) targets of Pum, we have used a combination of informatics and experimental approaches. Our first step to identify new Pum targets was to characterize and model the Pum binding sites. We then used our models to predict the presence of NREs in the 3&#x02032;UTRs of mRNAs coding for synaptic proteins. We validated several of these by in vitro binding assays. We then used an established in vivo functional assay <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> to demonstrate Pum-dependent repression via the predicted NRE in the 3&#x02032;UTR of <italic>dlg1</italic>. Finally we demonstrated that transgenic over-expression of Pum is sufficient to reduce endogenous levels of Dlg protein in Kenyon cell neurons of the mushroom body.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><p>As a first step to predict novel Pum targets, we attempted to model the known NREs. The known targets of Pum include <italic>hb</italic>, <italic>bcd</italic>, <italic>CycB</italic> and <italic>eIF-4E</italic>. At the time we initiated this study, the exact binding sites of Pum on <italic>eIF-4E</italic> and <italic>CycB</italic> were unclear <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. In contrast, the NREs in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> mRNAs are relatively well studied, with both in vitro binding assays and in vivo functional tests on wild-type and mutated sites <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The <italic>hb</italic> transcript contains two NREs and the <italic>bcd</italic> mRNA contains one copy of the NRE that is very similar to <italic>hb</italic> NREs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Sequences of Known NREs and Their Conservation Across Fly Species.</title><p>(A) Known NREs in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> as identified by Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> and <italic>CycB</italic> TCE (with flanking sequences) by Dalby and Glover <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dalby1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Deletion of the underlined sequence in the <italic>CycB</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR disrupts translation control. Conserved boxes in these sequences are in boldface. (B) Alignment of NREs in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> across several fly species. On the left are the gene names and species. In the middle are the Genbank accessions and the positions of the sequence segments shown in the alignment on the right. Box A and Box B are highlighted in bold face. Sequence alignment columns that are completely conserved are labeled with asterisks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g001"/></fig><p>As defined by Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, the NREs are 32-nucleotide sequences with two &#x0201c;boxes&#x0201d; that are well conserved across sites and between fly species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1</xref>). The two conserved boxes are often referred as Box A and Box B. Mutation and footprinting studies on <italic>hb</italic> NRE2 suggested that a GST-fused Pum RNA-binding domain contacts both Box A and Box B <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, consistent with the binding results by Zamore et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> on a 37-nt RNA sequence comprising one <italic>hb</italic> NRE and mutants thereof. Particularly, mutations in the last four nucleotides of Box B (UGUA, base 21&#x02013;24, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) appear to have the strongest effects on both Pum binding and in vivo function of the NRE, whereas many mutations around Box A appear to have weaker effects <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. <italic>hb</italic> NRE bases 17&#x02013;20 appear to be important for Pum to recruit Nos but not for Pum binding per se <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Recent results from a structural study of human pumilio-homology domain <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, a study of binding specificity and mRNA targets of a <italic>C. elegans</italic> PUF protein <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and a genome-wide identification of mRNAs associated with <italic>Drosophilia</italic> Pumilio <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, strongly indicate that Box B sequences are crucial for binding to Puf proteins. In the case of <italic>bcd</italic>, which contains a single NRE, there is a half-site shortly downstream containing Box B. The NRE-related boxes in <italic>bcd</italic> and <italic>hb</italic> are evolutionarily conserved across several <italic>Drosophila</italic> species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gamberi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-MacDonald1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>). We used these NREs, and their conservation, as starting points to better define a model for NRE prediction.</p><sec id="s2a"><title>NRE Models for Fly Species</title><p>We constructed three alternative models for Pum-binding sites, based on different assumptions. The first model is a simple consensus pattern, and the other two are based on positional weight matrices (PWM) <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Stormo1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Stormo2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The three alternative models of the NRE are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g002">Figure 2</xref>. NRE_PAT is a simple consensus of known NREs in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd,</italic> and translational control element (TCE) in <italic>CycB</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dalby1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. The conserved boxes in NREs suggest a pattern in which Box A precedes Box B. Both of the boxes may be important as previous studies suggested that Pum makes contact with both of them <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Murata1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The distance between Box A and Box B in <italic>bcd</italic> of some fly species is one base longer than <italic>melanogaster</italic>, suggesting that the distance between the two boxes may be flexible. <italic>CycB</italic> TCE also contains short sequence segments like Box A and Box B and the distance between them is 23 bp. Therefore, we arbitrarily set the distance between 3 to 45 bases, to reduce the chance of missing some possible functional sites.</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Models of NREs Constructed To Predict New Putative Pum-Binding Sites.</title><p>(A) Sequence pattern as a regular expression. [ACGT] {3, 45} matches any sequences from length 3 to 45. (B,C) Base-frequency matrices obtained using Gibbs Sampler with different parameter settings. Position 7 of NRE_M8 is a motif gap, which means the base in this position is irrelevant. Here we use DNA notation instead of RNA notation because the transcript sequences from the genome project are in DNA notation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g002"/></fig><p>NRE_M8 and NRE_M10 are frequency matrices generated by Gibbs Sampler (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>). NRE_M8 is based on the assumption that both Box A and Box B may bind Pum. We used the recursive mode of Gibbs Sampler to require each sequence to contain two to three binding sites. In the output, the program actually picked two sites in each sequence. When we required a longer motif length, the information content at the additional position was very low. Therefore, we stopped at this motif with seven valid positions and one gap. NRE_M10 is based on the assumption that only Box B is important for Pum binding. This was derived from the data of the human Pum-RNA crystal structure <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. We used the site sampler mode of the Gibbs program, which assumes that each sequence contains exactly one binding site. We picked the motif length 10 because this motif happened to cover Box B and four bases downstream, which contact Pum in the crystal structure. It is also worth noting that two of these four downstream bases are conserved across fly species in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> NREs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Prediction of New Pum Targets in Synaptic Genes</title><p>The predicted Pum targets among the 151 synaptic genes with the above three NRE models are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s007">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s008">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s009">S3</xref>, respectively. With NRE_PAT, only five transcripts/genes are predicted. Among them, the pattern match is conserved between <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> in only one gene, <italic>dlg1</italic> (transcript isoforms A and D, which contain identical 3&#x02032;UTRs). Conservation is unknown for two genes, <italic>AP-1 gamma</italic> and <italic>mam</italic>, because corresponding <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR sequences were not available at the time we initiated this study. Non-conserved predictions on <italic>CaMKII</italic> and <italic>EP2237</italic> could be false positives. However, it is also possible that the 3&#x02032;UTR sequences of those two genes are incomplete or inaccurate for <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> (at the time we initiate this study), resulting in the failure to find conserved sites.</p><p>With NRE_M8, 31 transcripts (28 genes) are predicted to be candidate Pum targets. Here, we require that a 3&#x02032;UTR sequence must contain at least two high-score sites to be considered as a candidate Pum target. Among them, 10 transcripts (8 genes) have at least two predicted sites that are conserved between the two fly species. With NRE_M10, 28 transcripts (25 genes) are predicted to be candidate Pum targets, among which 11 transcripts (9 genes) have at least one conserved site. Notably, <italic>dlg1</italic> gene is predicted to be a candidate Pum target all three NRE models. In addition, the target <italic>dlg1</italic> has also been previously suggested as a potential Pum target based on its presence in a collection of 1434 <italic>Drosophila</italic> genes containing the motif UGUAHAUA <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>In Vitro Validation of Predicted Pum Targets</title><p>Candidate memory genes from our previous studies <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> were sorted by their effect size (i.e., differential expression in microarray experiments). 12 transcripts (11 genes) with predicted Pum binding sites were chosen for further testing based on their ranking in the candidate memory gene list and their relevance to memory and/or synaptic functions as annotated in FlyBase. Among those, we successfully obtained the 3&#x02032;UTR sequence segments in 9 transcripts by PCR, to make templates for in vitro transcription. These target genes, their Pum-binding predictions, and the locations of tested 3&#x02032;UTR segments are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000026-t001">Table 1</xref>. Among these, the <italic>dlg1</italic> gene has predicted Pum binding sites in the 3&#x02032;UTR of two non-overlapping transcript isoforms (also refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s005">Figure S4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pcbi-1000026-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Genes (Transcripts) Selected for Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA)</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pcbi-1000026-t001-1" xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Gene Description</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Predictions</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">EMSA Results</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene Symbol</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FlyBase ID</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RepresentativeTranscript</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRE_PAT Match</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRE_M8 (cutoff&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;7.5, max&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10.97)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NRE_M10 (cutoff&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10, max&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;15.21)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe Position in 3UTR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent Binding</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binding Sites</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Ace</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0000024</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG17907-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.119 (751), 8.875 (814)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 9.798 (1265)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">o</xref>, 9.119 (1351)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.78 (814)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 10.34 (1229)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">722&#x02013;1095</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>AP-1gamma</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0030089</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG9113-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">122&#x02013;141 (GTTGT..9..ATTGTA)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.97 (122)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>, 8.873 (136)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>, 8.349 (240)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85&#x02013;191</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Csp</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0004179</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG6395-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.666 (109)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 8.872 (1050), 7.666 (1242)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 9.795 (1303), 9.119 (1519)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 7.666 (1561), 7.666 (1909)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.95 (87), 10.13 (1537)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1218&#x02013;1545</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>dlg1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0001624</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG1725-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1491&#x02013;1534 (GTTGT..33..ATTGTA)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8 (367)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 10.97 (1491)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 8.872 (1529)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.57 (367)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1485&#x02013;1539</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>dlg1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0001624</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG1725-RC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59 (277), 8.59 (783), 10.04 (793)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">744&#x02013;829</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>EP2237</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0043364</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG4427-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401&#x02013;443 (GTTGT..32..ATTGTA)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.12 (390)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.40 (318)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340&#x02013;514</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Gad1</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0004516</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG14994-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.872 (730), 8.595 (950)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">704&#x02013;973</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>mam</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0002643</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG8118-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">716&#x02013;735 (GTTGT..9..ATTGTA)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.795 (7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>, 9.8 (716)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>, 8.875 (1037)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.40 (1037)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">n</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">642&#x02013;1110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>shn</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBgn0003396</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CG7734-RA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.872 (480), 7.666 (835), 7.72 (913)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 8.875 (983)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 8.873 (1105)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.78 (895)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>, 14.78 (983)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">809&#x02013;1013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>Gene symbols, FlyBase IDs, and transcript IDs are from the Berkeley <italic>Drosophila</italic> Genome Project (BDGP) Release 3.1 annotation. Pattern-match predictions are represented as: <italic>start-end coordinates (matched sequence).</italic> The number between the dots represents the length of the sequence between the two boxes. Matrix predictions are represented as: <italic>score(coordinate).</italic> The coordinate corresponds to the first position in the matrix. The probe positions are shown as a coordinate range. All coordinates are referred to the stop codon (the first nucleotide of the stop codon as coordinate 1).</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><p>Superscripts in the predictions represent the conservation between <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>a</label><p>The predicted site is aligned with a predicted site in <italic>D. pseudoobscura.</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>o</label><p>The predicted site overlaps with a predicted site in <italic>D. pseudoobscura.</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>n</label><p>Corresponding 3&#x02032;UTR sequence in <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> is not available. The predicted sites in boldface are covered by the tested RNA probes.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We next sought to determine the binding specificity of the predicted NRE-like elements. To this end, we carried out electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) using purified GST-Pum, which bears the RNA-binding domain of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pum (amino acids 1091&#x02013;1533) fused with an N-terminal GST tag and has been shown to maintain the full binding activity of the wild-type Pum protein <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The second NRE element (NRE2) of <italic>hb</italic> served as a positive control for Pum binding, whereas a random control RNA sequence, CRS that does not resemble an NRE-like element served as a negative control. Under the experimental conditions used, GST-Pum bound to <italic>hb</italic> NRE2 with high affinity, but did not bind to the control RNA sequence CRS, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g003">Figure 3A</xref>. In a parallel control experiment in which GST-Pum was substituted by GST alone, no protein&#x02013;RNA complex between GST and <italic>hb</italic> NRE was formed, ruling out the possibility that the complex between GST-Pum and <italic>hb</italic> NRE was generated by non-specific binding of GST to RNA. We also note that, under our experimental conditions, only one complex was formed between GST-Pum and <italic>hb</italic> NRE as we increased the concentration of GST-Pum, consistent with the presence of a single Pum binding site in a single <italic>hb</italic> NRE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Binding of Pum to <italic>hb</italic> NRE2.</title><p>(A) EMSA showing the specific binding of recombinant <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pum to radiolabeled <italic>hb</italic> NRE2 RNA. A total of 10 fmol of radiolabeled hb-NRE2 or control CRS RNA was used in each lane. Various amounts of recombinant GST-Pum or GST control proteins were used in different lanes: 2 fmol in lanes 2, 5, and 9; 10 fmol in lanes 3, 6, and 10; 50 fmol in lanes 4, 7, and 11; no protein in lanes 1 and 8. (B) EMSA showing the complex formed between Pum and hb-NRE2 at a higher molar ratio of protein to RNA. A total of 10 fmol of radiolabelled hb-NRE2 RNA was used in each lane. Recombinant GST-Pum proteins used in lanes 1, 2, 3, and 4 were 0 fmol, 50 fmol, 500 fmol, and 5 pmol, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g003"/></fig><p>Next, we determined the binding specificity of the predicted NRE-like elements by EMSA. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g004">Figure 4A and 4B</xref>, Pum binds, albeit with different affinities, to all these predicted elements, except for <italic>dlg1</italic> isoform C, which was not bound by Pum at all, even at a high molar ratio of protein to RNA. However, <italic>dlg1</italic> transcript isoform C shares a different 3&#x02032;UTR sequence from <italic>dlg1</italic> transcript isoforms A and D. For the RNAs from <italic>hb</italic> NRE, <italic>dlg1</italic> isoforms A and D, and <italic>AP-1 gamma</italic>, only one complex was formed upon binding of Pum. For the remaining RNAs, two or more complexes were formed, suggesting the existence of more than one Pum-binding site.</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Binding of Pum to the Predicted NRE-Like Elements.</title><p>(A,B) A total of 10 fmol of radiolabeled RNA from the 3&#x02032;UTR of the predicted genes was used in each lane. For each RNA sample, recombinant GST-Pum proteins were added in three different amounts: 0 fmol, 50 fmol, and 150 fmol. Electrophoresis was carried out on a 5&#x00025; native polyacrylamide gel at 150 V at room temperature.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g004"/></fig><p>To evaluate the relative binding affinities of these NRE-like elements, we quantified the EMSA results on a phosphorimager (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000026-t001">Table 1</xref>). At the 5&#x02236;1 molar ratio of protein to RNA, 67.9&#x00025; of <italic>hb</italic> NRE was bound by Pum. Under the same experimental condition, greater than 50&#x00025; of the transcripts from <italic>dlg1</italic> (isoforms A and D), <italic>shn, Csp,</italic> and <italic>mam</italic> were bound by Pum, suggesting that NRE-like elements in these transcripts have strong Pum-binding activities comparable to <italic>hb</italic> NRE. On the other hand, at the same 5&#x02236;1 molar ratio of protein to RNA, transcripts from <italic>Ace, AP-1gamma, EP2237</italic>, and <italic>Gad1</italic> were largely unbound by Pum and showed weaker but substantial Pum-binding activities. We also tested Pum-binding activity of a 142-nt RNA fragment consisting of <italic>CycB</italic> TCE and flanking sequences (nts 400&#x02013;541 of 3&#x02032;UTR of <italic>CycB</italic> mRNA) and found that <italic>CycB</italic> TCE was able to bind to Pum with a much lower affinity compared to <italic>hb</italic> NRE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g004">Figure 4A</xref>, lanes 10&#x02013;12, and data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Model Evaluation with Binding Data</title><p>As a validation of our PWM models, we calculated the correlation coefficient between the prediction scores and the binding affinities. The correlation for NRE_M10 is statistically significant (cor&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.67, <italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.017) whereas the correlation for NRE_M8 is weaker and not statistically significant (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s002">Figure S1</xref> for details). This suggests that NRE_M10 is more accurate than NRE_M8, supporting the assumption behind NRE_M10, i.e., only Box B is important for Pum binding.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Expression Profiling of Putative Pum Targets During Memory Formation</title><p>While the validity of our model is also supported by our in vitro binding experiments, we decided to use an in vivo assay to validate our target prediction method for a few of the putative targets. Because we were interested in targets with potential relevance to behavioral plasticity, we decided first to quantify transcript levels for each candidate in response to behavioral training that induces long-term memory.</p><p>Expression profiling after experience-dependent memory formation indicated that the regulatory pathway for local translation (including Pum) is transcriptionally induced by spaced training <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus we reasoned that mRNA levels of some of Pum targets might also be regulated. Using quantitative (real time) PCR (QPCR), we measured expression levels after spaced versus massed training for each of the putative Pum targets that showed robust binding in vitro. Two of them, <italic>Ace</italic> and <italic>dlg1</italic>, were significantly induced 6 hours after spaced training (fold change&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.58, <italic>N</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8, <italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.0036 for <italic>Ace</italic>; fold change&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.56, <italic>N</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8, <italic>p</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.0068 for <italic>dlg1</italic>). While we do not understand why transcriptional responses for Pum's targets are in the same direction as that of Pum, this may reflect global transcriptional increases versus local translational repression (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">Discussion</xref>). These two candidate target genes were chosen for in vivo assays.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>In Vivo Confirmation of Predicted NRE Elements</title><p>To validate our target prediction method in vivo, we chose to use a Pum response assay described previously <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. This assay relies upon the requirement that maternally supplied <italic>hb</italic> mRNA be repressed by Pum/Nos in posterior regions of the early embryo. We started with a canonical genomic <italic>hb</italic> rescuing transgene in which the endogenous NRE motifs were deleted. In the absence of functional NRE elements, this construct causes a dominant sterility in transgenic females due to ectopic <italic>hb</italic> translation in the posterior half of the embryos produced. Such embryos are unable to form abdominal segments. Insertion of a functional NRE motif into this canonical construct restores Pum-mediated repression in the posterior, allowing production of viable progeny. Using this strategy, we tested the functional capacity of the predicted NRE motifs from <italic>Ace</italic> and <italic>dlg1</italic>. We chose these two putative targets because they showed relatively strong in vitro binding and also because both transcripts are induced by spaced training.</p><p>We generated a series of <italic>hb</italic>-transgene constructs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g005">Figure 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s010">Table S4</xref>) in which the two endogenous <italic>hb</italic> NREs had either been deleted entirely (<bold>hb&#x00394;</bold>), replaced with a single <italic>hb</italic> NRE, NRE2 (<bold>hb2</bold>), had both <italic>hb</italic> NRE elements re-inserted (<bold>hb1,2</bold>), replaced with putative NRE elements from <italic>Ace</italic> or <italic>dlg1</italic> genes (<bold>Ace</bold> or <bold>dlg1</bold>), or replaced with an anti-sense version of the predicted <italic>dlg1</italic> NRE (<bold>dlg1-anti</bold>). We found that the predicted NRE from <italic>dlg1</italic> is sufficient to partially restore abdominal patterning when compared with <bold>hb1,2</bold> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g005">Figure 5A and 5B</xref>), which provided full rescue as in Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. It is worth noting that the rescue observed with the single <italic>dlg1</italic> NRE is superior to that observed with a single copy of the <italic>hb</italic> NRE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g005">Figure 5A and 5B</xref>). Consistent with a previous observation by Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, a single <italic>hb</italic> NRE (<bold>hb2</bold>) yields partial rescue. In contrast, control transgenic lines in which no functional NRE was provided, or in which the <italic>dlg1</italic> NRE was inserted in opposite orientation (<bold>dlg1-anti</bold>) generate progeny nearly devoid of abdominal segments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g005">Figures 5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">6B</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s010">Table S4</xref>). It is also worth mentioning that we failed to observe a rescue of normal abdominal segmentation when using another <italic>hb</italic>-transgene construct (<bold>dlg1-full</bold>), in which the two endogenous <italic>hb</italic> NREs are replaced by a longer version of the transcript, a 1.2-kb sequence including the predicted NRE element from the 2.8-kb sequence of <italic>dlg1</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s010">Table S4</xref>). The lack of rescue with this construct may be caused by the artificial context of the transcript resulting from insertion of such a large heterologous fragment into the <italic>hb</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR. We also failed to observe any rescue when using a <italic>hb</italic>-transgene construct in which <italic>hb</italic> NREs were replaced with putative NRE elements from <italic>Ace,</italic> indicating <italic>Ace</italic> might not function as a Pum target in an in vivo context despite positive results in computational search and biochemical validation.</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>In Vivo Confirmation of Predicted NRE Elements.</title><p>(A) Cartoon representations of the <italic>hb</italic>-transgene constructs and representative examples from cuticle preparations of corresponding transformant lines, showing normal/abnormal or rescued/partial rescued abdominal segmentation. Transgenic lines containing both <italic>hb</italic> NREs either in the normal context (wild type) or reinserted into the deletion construct (hb1,2) are fully regulated by Pum and yield embryos with the normal complement of 8 abdominal segments. Deletion of both of these NREs (hb&#x00394;) prevents Pum-dependent translational repression leading to complete absence of abdominal segmentation. Insertion of either one <italic>hb</italic> NRE (hb2) or the predicted NRE from <italic>dlg1</italic> (dlg1) are each sufficient to partially restore abdominal development. (B) The average numbers of abdominal segments are shown for each of four transformant lines resulting from each of the <italic>hb</italic>-transgene constructs. A total of 72&#x02013;140 embryos of each transformant line were analyzed to count the number of abdominal segments to generate the mean number. (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s010">Table S4</xref> for frequency distribution of each line).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g005"/></fig><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Dlg Is Repressed by Over-Expression of Pum in MB Kenyon Cells.</title><p>MB expressing Gal4 line (OK107) was used to drive expression of both UAS-mCD8::GFP (green) and UAS-Pum transgenes. Optical sections of the MB lobes (A&#x02013;F) or MB peduncle (G&#x02013;L) are shown. In wild type (A&#x02013;C, G&#x02013;I), Dlg expression (red) is detected both in MB lobes and AL (A) as well as in the MB peduncle (G). In contrast, Dlg expression is dramatically reduced in the MB lobes (D) and peduncle (J) of Pum over-expressing MBs. AL glomeruli, also stained by Dlg antibody, serve as an internal control. We also noticed that when Pumilio is over-expressed in MB, there is MB developmental defect in MB lobe structure (visualized by GFP and shown in [E]). Despite this, GFP levels appear normal in the peduncle (K). Asterisk indicates peduncles where Dlg expression can be detected in wild type MB but is dramatically reduced in Pum over-expressing MB. As an additional confirmation, we used a series of Gal4 drivers that express preferentially in subsets of MB neurons (data not shown). Among all these Gal4 drivers, OK107 produced the strongest downregulation of Dlg as stated above. 238Y and c739 produced the second strongest effects: Dlg expression level is significantly reduced in the peduncle of the UAS-Pum; 238Y brains and is dramatically reduced in the &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; lobes of the UAS-Pum; c739 brains. We did not observe MB structural defects with either of these lines We also did not observe effects with Pum over-expression using c747 or c309. This likely is due either to differences in expression levels, timing or neuron number. Pum over-expression crosses using elav, MJ85b, 247 and 201Y and GH146 Gal4 lines were lethal during development.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>In Vivo Confirmation of <italic>dlg1</italic> as a Target of Pumilio in a Neuronal Context</title><p>The above data support the conclusion that the <italic>dlg1</italic> mRNA contains a Pum binding site that can confer translational repression to a heterologous reporter system in the embryo. We next sought to test whether the endogenous <italic>dlg1</italic> mRNA can be regulated by Pumilio in a relevant neuronal context. Because of our interest in olfactory memory, we chose to test for Pum-mediated regulation of Dlg in the adult mushroom body (MB), which is an anatomical site of memory storage <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Heisenberg1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Margulies1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. We first used a monoclonal antibody against Dlg to examine the distribution of Dlg protein in brains of wild-type animals. Consistent with Ruiz-Canada et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-RuizCanada1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, we found that Dlg is widely distributed in the adult brain, with elevated levels in antenna lobes (AL) and mushroom bodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). We then tested whether transgenic over-expression of Pum in MB was sufficient to reduce the endogenous Dlg expression. To do this, we used a MB Gal4 enhancer trap line OK107 <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Connolly1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> to drive the expression of both UAS-mCD8::GFP and UAS-Pumilio transgenes in the same brain. The GFP expression permitted independent visualization of the MB neuronal architecture and also served as an internal control for the distribution of Dlg.</p><p>Our imaging studies support two conclusions. First, we found that transgenic expression of Pum in MB Kenyon cells results in a dramatic reduction of Dlg expression levels. Importantly Dlg expression in AL appears unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). In addition, the GFP expression in MB neurons appears at normal levels. This observation strongly supports the hypothesis that endogenous Dlg expression can be repressed by Pum in the CNS. Second, we also noticed that transgenic over-expression of Pum causes a severe defect in the elaboration of the axonal projections of MB neurons. This is evident in the expression of UAS-mCD8::GFP, which permits visualization of the entire MB neuronal architecture. In wild type animals, MB Kenyon cell axons dive ventrally and anteriorly along the peduncle. They then bifurcate into distinct vertical (&#x003b1; and &#x003b1;&#x02032;) and horizontal (&#x003b2;, &#x003b2;&#x02032; and &#x003b3;) lobes, which contain the axon terminals. In contrast, the MBs of Pum over-expressing animals do not form normal lobe structures. Instead, the axons appear to prematurely terminate just medial to the peduncle.</p><p>The above observation suggests the interesting possibility that Pum normally plays a key developmental role in elaboration of MB structure. While we cannot rule out neo-morphic effects of Pum over-expression, these findings nevertheless are consistent with the previous observations of Pum's role in dendrite morphology <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Ye1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. At the same time, however, we were concerned that the decreased accumulation of Dlg protein that we observed with Pum over-expression could be an indirect consequence of the MB structural defects. We used several strategies to rule this out. First, we made careful observation of Dlg expression levels in the peduncle in both wild type control and Pum over-expressing brains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6A</xref>). Unlike the lobes, which are largely absent from these animals, the peduncle is intact. GFP expression in the peduncle was used as a reference. Second, we used a monoclonal antibody against FasII, which like Dlg, is expressed at elevated levels in MB Kenyon cell neurons (although mostly &#x003b1;/&#x003b2;). This permitted a second independent means to image the MB of the same animals and also provided expression of a second endogenous protein as a control. Both of these experiments support the conclusion that Dlg expression per se is reduced in Pum over-expressing animals because both GFP and FasII protein levels are un-altered in the residual lobes and in the peduncle (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g007">Figure 7</xref>). Finally, we used several additional MB expressing Gal4 drivers to confirm the key observation that ectopic Pum can down regulate Dlg (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6</xref> legend; data not shown). The magnitude of the effects on Dlg expression varied depending on expression levels, timing and number/type of MB neurons labeled. Nevertheless, we observed decreased Dlg immuno-labeling both with MB Gal4 line C739 and 238Y (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">Figure 6</xref> legend and data not shown).</p><fig id="pcbi-1000026-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000026.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>FasII Levels Appear Unaffected by Pum Over-Expression.</title><p>MB expressing Gal4 line (OK107) was used to drive expression of both UAS-mCD8::GFP (green) and UAS-Pum transgenes. Optical sections of the MB lobes (A&#x02013;F) or MB peduncle (G&#x02013;L) are shown. In both wild type (A&#x02013;C and G&#x02013;I) and Pum over-expressing MBs (D&#x02013;F and J&#x02013;L), FasII expression is detected both in MB lobes (&#x003b1;/&#x003b2; [A] and [D]) as well as in the MB peduncle ([G] and [J]). The MB developmental defect in Pum over-expressing MBs can be visualized by both GFP (E) and FasII staining (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.g007"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The bioinformatic prediction of mRNA targets for sequence-specific RNA binding proteins continues to be a significant challenge. In most cases, biologically relevant motifs are hard to define, in part due to the unknown impact of secondary structure. This is confounded by the fact that in vivo assays to validate predictions are often not trivial. One approach to identify targets is to use genome-wide detection of mRNAs that directly associate with an RNA-binding protein. This approach was used with success <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> to identify putative Pum-associated mRNAs from ovaries and early embryos. In this study, we have taken a different approach to identify neuronal targets that might underlie Pum's role in memory. We took advantage of: (1) the availability of well characterized structural and functional information about Pum-HD:RNA interactions; (2) several conserved NRE elements that had been described for the <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> genes; (3) the availability of a robust in vivo functional assay <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, and (4) in vivo imaging of one target gene's expression to validate our predictions. We have identified a group of putative neuronal targets of Pum, including <italic>dlg1</italic> and <italic>Ace</italic>, both of which are also induced during memory consolidation. In the case of <italic>dlg1</italic>, the identified NRE appears capable of functioning both in a heterologous in vivo context of the early embryo and an endogenous one in the adult brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g005">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g006">6</xref>).</p><p>Our results also suggest that the binding specificity of Pum is conserved between <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mammals, as previously noted in Wang et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, which is consistent with the observations that human Pum2 binds to the <italic>Drosophila</italic> NRE sequence <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Moore1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Fox1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. First, NRE_M10, which is based on assumptions derived from the human Pum-RNA crystal structure, performed best among the three motif models constructed with known Pum targets in flies. Second, a motif derived from mouse PUM2 SELEX data, MmSelex_M8 (&#x0201c;Conservation of Pum binding specificity between fly and mouse&#x0201d; in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s001">Text S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s003">Figure S2</xref>), fit well with the <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pum binding data from EMSA. Furthermore, this conservation of Pum binding specificity may be extended to non-mammalian vertebrates, as <italic>Xenopus</italic> Pum has been shown to bind <italic>Drosophila hb</italic> NRE <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Nakahata1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. In fact, the RNA-binding domain of <italic>Drosophila</italic> Pum is very similar to that in human, mouse and <italic>Xenopus</italic> (amino acid identity &#x02265;78&#x00025;).</p><p>The fact that prediction scores of NRE_M10 and MmSelex_M8 are well correlated with in vitro binding data demonstrates the validity of these two models for Pum binding site prediction. The predicted hits by these two models in the synaptic gene set are significantly higher than random (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s004">Figure S3</xref>), further demonstrating their validity and also suggesting that a number of synaptic genes are likely regulated by Pum. In the case of <italic>dlg1</italic>, our in vivo evidence indicates that the predicted NRE can function, not only in context of the <italic>hb</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR, but also in CNS while Pum is over-expressed.</p><p>Comparing our synaptic gene set with the pulled-down targets from Gerber et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 27 (18&#x00025;) genes are in the adult specific target list. Only one gene overlaps with the embryo specific targets, presumably because the embryo specific target list is much smaller. Our predicted Pum targets using NRE_M10 and mmSelex_M8 are significantly enriched with experimentally pulled-down targets (36&#x00025; and 30&#x00025;, respectively, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s006">Figure S5</xref> for more details). Although our NRE models, NRE_M10 and mmSelex_M8 were constructed from a very limited number of training sequences, the motif patterns match closely with the consensus Pum binding site published in Gerber et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, especially in the 8-nt core motif. These all validate the effectiveness of our method. Of course, further improvement can be made with more high confidence training sequences.</p><p>Studies in diverse organisms strongly indicate that sequences around BoxB play a major role in binding to Puf proteins <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Bernstein1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> although BoxA may affect the binding affinity to some extent <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Cheong1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Interestingly, the binding specificities appear to vary among Puf family members even though their RNA-binding domains are highly conserved. For example, Puf3, Puf4 and Puf5 in yeast appear to recognize similar motifs but in different lengths <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. A recent finding by Opperman et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Opperman1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> shed a light on this. It is indicated that small structural difference in the RNA-binding domain may require extra spacer nucleotides in the binding site. This BoxB related motif, hallmarked with UGUA tetranucleotide, may represent the most prevalent binding sites for Pum or even Puf family proteins. However, other types of binding sites may also exist as we will discuss below.</p><p>Notably, Pum binds to a 142-nt RNA harboring <italic>CycB</italic> TCE with a lower affinity than <italic>hb</italic> NRE under our experimental conditions. <italic>CycB</italic> TCE was initially proposed due to its resemblance to <italic>bcd</italic> and <italic>hb</italic> NRE, and was required for translational repression control <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dalby1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. This cis-acting element was able to bind GST-Pum <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, but not the purified Pum RBD or native embryonic extracts <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Indeed, <italic>CycB</italic> TCE has a lower score according to our matrix. A new element downstream of TCE has recently been proposed and been shown to bind to Pum in gel mobility shift experiments and, when substituted for the native <italic>hb</italic> NRE in a chimeric <italic>hb</italic> mRNA, was able to mediate <italic>CycB</italic>-like regulation on <italic>hb</italic> mRNA <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Intriguingly, our matrix also predicts a Pum-binding site with high score (<named-content content-type="gene">ATTGTGCAAA</named-content>, nts 561&#x02013;570 of 3&#x02032;UTR of <italic>CycB</italic> mRNA) in the RNA fragment used in these experiments. Our predicted site is close to the NRE element proposed by Kadyrova and colleagues, but not the same. Further work needs to be done to address this discrepancy. It is also worth mentioning that there are several significant differences between regulation of <italic>CycB</italic> mRNA and <italic>hb</italic>/<italic>bcd</italic> mRNAs <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. In contrast with <italic>bcd</italic> and <italic>hb</italic>, for example, regulation of <italic>CycB</italic> is Brat-independent. Kadyrova et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> have demonstrated that in the case of <italic>CycB</italic>, Pum binding seems important only to recruit Nanos, because artificially tethering Nanos to the 3&#x02032;UTR bypasses the requirement for Pum binding. This is in contrast to Pum's regulation of <italic>hb</italic>. Thus it seems that there are significant differences between the Pum-binding sites in <italic>CycB</italic> mRNA and those in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> mRNAs, as proposed previously <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Related to that, in the minimal 51 nt eIF-4E 3&#x02032;UTR sequence bound by Pum <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, only one binding site is predicted by NRE_M8 with a score just above the cutoff value 7.5, suggesting the Pum binding to eIF-4E 3&#x02032;UTR may be also different from <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic>. Discovery of additional Pum targets from a variety of cell types and biological contexts may uncover the relationship between NRE sequence and regulatory mechanism.</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to characterize and predict Pum-binding sites with a PWM approach, which is typically more sensitive and more precise than consensus methods <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Stormo2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Our in vitro binding assay of Pum on a subset of the predicted targets provides a measure of validation of our motif models. Like Pum, two of these targets, <italic>Ace</italic> and <italic>dlg1</italic>, also appear to be transcriptionally induced after spaced training relative to massed training, suggesting that these are relevant targets for memory formation. We do not know why both a translational repressor and its putative targets are transcriptionally induced. It may be that transcripts are increased on a cell-wide level, while translation is spatially regulated within neurons. In the case of <italic>dlg1</italic>, our in vivo evidence supports the conclusion that the predicted NRE can mediate Pum-dependent repression both when it is in the context of the <italic>hb</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR and in the endogenous <italic>dlg1</italic> transcript in the CNS. Thus, our findings directly predict that <italic>dlg1</italic> is a synaptic target of Pum.</p><p>Dlg is the sole <italic>Drosophila</italic> member of a family of membrane-associated guanylate kinases (MAGUKs) that in mammals have been shown to play a key role in assembling the post-synaptic density in glutamatergic synapses. In <italic>Drosophila</italic>, Dlg expression is both pre- and post-synaptic at Type I boutons at the NMJ, and mutants exhibit post-synaptic structural defects as well as increased transmitter release <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Budnik1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Guan1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Dlg is thought to play a key role in clustering GluRIIB receptors at the NMJ <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> as well as Shaker K<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> channels throughout the CNS <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-RuizCanada1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>.</p><p>Like Dlg, Pum also appears to have both pre- and post-synaptic effects at the NMJ and is co-localized with Dlg at Type I boutons <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In addition to morphological effects on synapse structure, Pum appears to regulate excitability via an effect on expression of <italic>para</italic> Na<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> channels <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Mee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Schweers1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Baines1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The regulation of <italic>para</italic> may be direct, or may depend upon Pum's putative role in regulating translation of eIF-4E <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Menon1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Pum expression itself is activity-induced and is induced by behavioral training that results in long-term memory <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Mee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>,<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus, one reasonable hypothesis is that activity-dependent increases in Pum expression play a homeostatic role by reducing excitability via repression of <italic>para</italic>
<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Baines1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. <italic>para</italic> is in our list of synaptic genes, yet our models did not predict any Pum binding sites in its 3&#x02032;UTR. That is not surprising since Mee et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Mee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> reported NRE-like sequence located in its 5&#x02032;UTR. Therefore, a different mechanism may be involved in the regulation of <italic>para</italic> by Pum.</p><p>Our findings suggest that an additional role of Pum is direct regulation of <italic>dlg1</italic> expression, thereby antagonizing the effects of Dlg on neuronal structure and/or function. We do not yet know whether other classic factors (Nanos and Brat) that cooperate with Pum in early embryos are also required in the translational control of Dlg in neurons. Further investigation also will be required to separate the roles of Pum in neuronal development and memory formation. Ultimate confirmation that Pum-dependent repression of <italic>dlg1</italic> and the other predicted NRE-containing genes underlies Pum's role in neuronal structure, function and memory will also require additional examination.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Synaptic Gene Collection</title><p>Synaptic genes were collected based on GeneOntology (GO) terms in the Berkeley <italic>Drosophila</italic> Genome Project (BDGP, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fruitfly.org/">http://www.fruitfly.org/</ext-link>) Release 3.1 annotation and keyword search in the FlyBase Vocabulary Report (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://flybase.org/">http://flybase.org/</ext-link>) of gene expression. GO terms involved in neurotransmitter metabolism were not considered to relate directly to synaptic functions, and were thus excluded. 68 genes were obtained from the GO annotation and 132 genes were obtained from FlyBase search using the keyword &#x0201c;synapse.&#x0201d; Among those, a total of 151 genes were mapped to Release 3.1 <italic>Drosophila</italic> genome (with CG ID) and were used for further analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s011">Table S5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>3&#x02032;UTR Sequence Collection</title><p>Sequences of mRNA or genomic DNA that contain complete 3&#x02032;UTRs of <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> from different fly species were retrieved from GenBank. The GenBank accessions are listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1B</xref>.</p><p>The 3&#x02032;UTR sequences of all annotated genes for <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> were retrieved from BDGP Release 3.1 annotation. Putative <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR sequences were obtained based on whole-genome alignment between <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> produced by the BDGP at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pipeline.lbl.gov/">http://pipeline.lbl.gov/</ext-link>). Distinct 3&#x02032;UTR sequences of the mapped 151 synaptic genes are included in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s007">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s008">S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s009">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s010">S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s011">S5</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Construction of Fly NRE Matrix Models</title><p>The Gibbs Sampler program (<xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Lawrence1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>; also refer to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bayesweb.wadsworth.org/gibbs/gibbs.html">http://bayesweb.wadsworth.org/gibbs/gibbs.html</ext-link>) obtained from C. E. Lawrence's group was used to perform local multiple sequence alignment to identify the motif model. The base-frequency matrix output from the program was converted into the log-odds PWM with a background nucleotide frequency derived from all 3&#x02032;UTRs in the genome of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, i.e.,<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.e001.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula>where <italic>w<sub>b,j</sub></italic> is the matrix weight for base <italic>b</italic> at position <italic>j</italic>, <italic>f<sub>b,j</sub></italic> is the frequency of base <italic>b</italic> at position <italic>j</italic> and <italic>p<sub>b</sub></italic> is the background frequency of base <italic>b</italic>. <italic>b</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;A, C, G or T, <italic>j</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1 &#x02026; <italic>n</italic> for a PWM of length <italic>n</italic>.</p><p>Input sequences to Gibbs Sampler included known NREs in <italic>hb</italic> and <italic>bcd</italic> of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> and their corresponding sequence segments in other fly species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g001">Figure 1B</xref>, in DNA letters without gaps). 3&#x02032;UTR sequences for <italic>CycB</italic> (<italic>melanogaster</italic> and <italic>pseudoobscura</italic>) and <italic>eIF-4E</italic> (<italic>melanogaster</italic> only) were also included.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Search for New Pum Targets</title><p>Pattern search was implemented with a Perl script as a regular expression match. Weight matrix scan on sequences was performed with an R script. For a PWM of length <italic>n</italic>, the score of a target sequence segment <italic>t&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;b<sub>1</sub>b<sub>2</sub> &#x02026; b<sub>n</sub></italic>, is:<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.e002.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula>where <italic>j</italic> is the position in the PWM, <italic>b<sub>j</sub></italic> is the <italic>j</italic>
<sup>th</sup> base of the target sequence.</p><p>We searched in the 3&#x02032;UTR sequences of all 151 synaptic genes, including their distinct splicing variants in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>. The matrix score cutoff was selected so that most of the known NREs scored above the threshold. Corresponding putative 3&#x02032;UTR sequences of <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> were also searched when available. We define a predicted site in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> as conserved if this site is aligned or overlaps with a predicted site in <italic>D. pseudoobscura</italic> in the LAGAN alignment provided by BDGP.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Purification of GST-PUM</title><p>The plasmid R6646 that encodes amino acids 1091&#x02013;1533 of <italic>Drosoplila</italic> Pum as a fusion with GST <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> was a gift from Dr. Robin Wharton. The protein was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> and purified by affinity chromatography on glutathione-Sepharose (Amersham Biosciences) by standard procedures.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>In Vitro Transcription</title><p>Transcription templates for the predicted NRE-like elements were obtained by PCR from <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> genomic DNA. A T7 promoter was added at the 5&#x02032; terminus of the template by PCR. PCR products were purified and used as templates for in vitro transcription, which was done as described <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Clarke1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. RNA transcripts were purified by electrophoresis on an 8&#x00025; or 4.5&#x00025; polyacrylamide/7M urea gel.</p></sec><sec id="s4g"><title>EMSA</title><p>EMSA was done as described <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The <italic>hunchback</italic> NRE2 sequence used was <named-content content-type="gene">AUUAUUUUGUUGUCGAAAAUUGUACAUAAGCC</named-content>. The random control RNA sequence (CRS) is <named-content content-type="gene">GGUAGUGCAUACAACUUCCUU</named-content>. Binding reactions were carried out by mixing 10 fmol radiolabeled RNA with variable amounts of purified GST-Pum in a 10 &#x003bc;l binding buffer containing 0.1 mg/ml BSA, 10 mM Hepes/KOH pH 7.4, 50 mM KCl, 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 0.1 mg/ml yeast tRNA, 2 mM dithiothreitol, 0.01&#x00025; (w/v) Tween-20, 0.2 U rRNAsin (Promega), and 10&#x00025; (v/v) glycerol. The protein-RNA complexes were allowed to form for 20 min at room temperature, followed by electrophoresis on a 5&#x00025; non-denaturing acrylamide gel in 1&#x000d7; TBE buffer. The gel was dried, followed by autoradiography at &#x02212;70&#x000b0;C or quantification on a phosphorimager (Fuji).</p></sec><sec id="s4h"><title>Quantitative PCR</title><p>RNA isolations were performed with Trizol (Invitrogen) as described before <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, with the following modifications. After the Trizol step, samples were treated with DNase I (Promega, 5 U) for 30 min (37&#x000b0;C) and then were extracted with phenol/chloroform/iso-amyl alcohol (Invitrogen), precipitated with ethanol, and resuspended in DEPC-treated water. RNA quality was tested using an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 and RNA 6000 Nano Chips. Reverse transcription reactions were performed with 5.0 &#x000b5;g RNA per reaction with an oligo dT primer and Taqman reverse transcription reagents (Applied Biosystems) in 100 &#x000b5;l total volume. PCR quantification was performed by using 4 &#x000b5;l of the above RT product per reaction on a real-time PCR machine (7900 HT, Applied Biosystems) using Taqman probe and Taqman reagents (Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer's protocols. Gene-specific primers and Taqman probes had the following sequences:</p><p>Ace: primers: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-GCACTACCCAAGACAAATTTTATCGAAA-3&#x02032;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-GCCCCGTACTACGCTTACAA-3&#x02032;</named-content>; probe: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CACATTTTCGATCGATTCTT-3&#x02032;</named-content>
</p><p>dlg1: primers: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-ATCCGCATAATAATGTAAACTACGACAGAA-3&#x02032;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-ACTCATTATATAGGTTTAAATCAACGCGAfCAA-3&#x02032;</named-content>; probe: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CAAATTCAATTTCTCCTTTTTTCC-3&#x02032;</named-content>
</p><p>TBP: primers: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-GCATCATCCAAAAGCTCGGTTT-3&#x02032;</named-content> and <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-GAGCCGACCATGTTTTGAATCTTAA-3&#x02032;</named-content>; probe: <named-content content-type="gene">5&#x02032;-CCCTGCAAAGTTCC-3&#x02032;</named-content>
</p><p>Prior to QPCR quantification of Pum targets, all primers and probes underwent the linearity test using 1, 2 and 4 &#x000b5;g RNA for RT reaction. Expression levels were normalized to Drosophila TBP transcript levels. TBP was confirmed as an unchanged control by comparing in excess of 100 RNA extractions each after spaced and massed training (data not shown). All reactions were done in parallel by using at least eight independent RNA isolations for each group, with each RNA isolate being assayed once. Normalized threshold values (Ct) were subjected to parametric t-tests, with significance levels set at alpha&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="s4i"><title>In Vivo Assay for NRE Function</title><p>The in vivo function of the predicted NRE-like elements was tested as described by Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Briefly, the selected NRE-like elements and control DNA were each cloned and inserted into the SpeI site of plasmid p1809, which bears a <italic>hunchback</italic> genomic rescuing construct with a deletion of NRE elements. An Asp718I-BamHI fragment containing each modified <italic>hunchback</italic> gene was cut out from the resulting plasmid and inserted into the P-element transformation vector CaSpeR4 digested with the same restriction enzymes. The resulting constructs were injected separately into w<sup>1118</sup>(isoCJ1) <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> recipient embryos and transformant lines were isolated by standard procedures via the BestGene, Inc.. In all cases, only male progeny were bred to avoid selecting non-expressing inserts. For each modified <italic>hunchback</italic> gene, four independent transformant lines were analyzed for the effects on segmentation pattern in embryos. NRE function in each line was tested by collecting embryos from heterozygous females. Cuticle preparations were analyzed according to Wharton and Struhl <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4j"><title>Flystocks and Crosses</title><p>A stock (5137; OK107) which is homozygous for both MB-specific Gal4 driver OK107 (on chromosome IV) and UAS-mCD8::GFP (on chromosome II) was crossed with wild type w<sup>1118</sup>(isoCJ1) or UAS-Pumilio (on chromosome II) homozygotes flies.</p></sec><sec id="s4k"><title>Immunohistochemistry and Image Acquisition and Processing</title><p>Adult brains were dissected in 1&#x000d7; PBS, fixed in 1&#x000d7; PBS containing 4&#x00025; formaldehyde for 30 minutes, and blocked in penetration/blocking buffer consisting of 1&#x000d7; PBS, 2&#x00025; Triton and 10&#x00025; normal goat serum (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Cat. 005-000-121) for 2 hours at 4&#x000b0;C. Then dissected brains were placed in primary antibody (1:20 dilution in Dilution Buffer containing 0.25&#x00025; Triton and 1&#x00025; normal goat serum in 1&#x000d7; PBS) for overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. After washing by Washing Buffer (1&#x00025; Triton, 3&#x00025; NaCl in 1&#x000d7; PBS) for 4&#x000d7;10 minutes in room temperature, dissected brains were placed in secondary antibody (1:200 dilution in Dilution Buffer) for overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The following antibodies were used: monoclonal anti-discs large-s antibody 4F3 (Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank at the University of Iowa) as primary antibody for Dlg staining, monoclonal anti-Fasciclin II-s antibody 1D4 (Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank at the University of Iowa) as primary antibody for FasII staining, Cy3 conjugated AffniPure Goat Anti-Mouse IgG (H&#x0002b;L) (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Cat. 115-165-003) as secondary antibody. Finally, the brains were washed by washing buffer for 4&#x000d7;10 minutes at room temperature, treated with FocusClear (CelExplorer Labs, Cat. FC-101) for 10 minutes and mounted onto slides with MountClear (CelExplorer Labs, Cat. MC-301).</p><p>Confocal stacks of brains were acquired using a ZEISS LSM 510 confocal microscope. Following confocal settings were used: 40&#x000d7; water immersion lens, 1 &#x000b5;m spacing in the <italic>z</italic>-axis and 1024&#x000d7;1024 resolution in <italic>x</italic>- and <italic>y</italic>-axes. The Cy3 signal is captured by HeNe1 543nm laser and GFP signal is captured by Argon/2 488nm laser. All brains were scanned from the anterior to the posterior to ensure good resolution of MB. The raw data were processed by LSM Image Browser Rel.4.2 (ZEISS) and further arranged into figures by Adobe Photoshop CS2.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s001"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>Supplementary Material</p><p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s002"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>Correlation Between Matrix Prediction Scores and Pum-Binding Affinities. The abscissa is the measured percentage binding of Pum to the mRNA target. The ordinate is the prediction score, which is the maximum matrix score of all the sites in a sequence. The 12 data points represent 12 mRNA sequences (nine test sequences in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000026-t001">Table 1</xref> and three control sequences). The Pearson correlation coefficient (cor) and its p-value are shown in the upper left corner. (A) Correlation for matrix NRE_M8. (B) Correlation for matrix NRE_M10.</p><p>(0.16 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s003"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>MmSelex_M8 Matrix and the Correlation of Its Prediction Scores to Pum-Binding Affinities. (A) Base-frequency matrices obtained using Gibbs Sampler with mouse SELEX sequence data from White et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-White1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Position 5 is a motif gap as in Gibbs output, which means that the base in this position is irrelevant. DNA notation is used as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000026-g002">Figure 2</xref>. (B) Correlation between matrix prediction scores and Pum-binding affinities for MmSelex_M8. Notations are the same as in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000026.s002">Figure S1</xref>.</p><p>(0.19 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s004"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>Estimation of False Positives with Random Shuffle Tests on the 151 Synaptic Genes. Shuffling times n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;500. (A) Matrix NRE_M10. (B) Matrix MmSelex_M8. The gray bars represent the hits with the original matrix. The black bars represent the average hits with randomly shuffled matrices. The error bar is the standard deviation across the 500 shuffling tests.</p><p>(0.21 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s005"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>dlg1 Gene Structure as Shown in the FlyBase Genome Browser. Transcript dlg1-RA and dlg1-RC are located on non-overlapping regions on the fly genome.</p><p>(0.06 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s005.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s006"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>Comparison of the Overlap of Our Pum Target Predictions with the Adult Specific Targets from Gerber et al. <xref rid="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> in the Synaptic Gene Set. Pred&#x0002b; and Pred&#x02212; represent the number of our positive or negative prediction, respectively. PD&#x0002b; and PD&#x02212; represent the number of positive or negative pulled-down targets from Gerber et al. (2006), respectively.</p><p>(0.09 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s006.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s007"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>NRE_PAT Predictions</p><p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s007.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s008"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>NRE_M8 Predictions</p><p>(0.03 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s008.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s009"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>NRE_M10 Predictions</p><p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s009.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s010"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>Segmentation Pattern in Embryos of Modified Hunchback Gene Transformant Lines</p><p>(0.02 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s010.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pcbi.1000026.s011"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p>Synaptic Gene List</p><p>(0.04 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pcbi.1000026.s011.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Robin P. Wharton for providing the plasmid R6646 and p1809 and for sharing a manuscript prior to publication, Dr. Richard Bains for providing the UAS-Pumilio fly stock, and Dr. Ann-Shyn Chiang for providing the 5137;OK107 fly stock. The Dlg and FasII monoclonal antibody developed by Dr. Corey S. Goodman's lab was obtained from the Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank developed under the auspices of the NICHD and maintained by the University of Iowa, Department of Biological Sciences.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>This project was supported by funds to JD, TT, and MQZ from Dart Neuroscience. JD is supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant 25630311 as well as by funds from the BYI and HFSP. TT is supported by NIH grant 25090401 and 25250401. Q-SZ and ARK are supported by NIH grant GM42699. MQZ is supported by NIH grant HG001696. WL is supported by the Graduate Program in Molecular and Cellular Biology, State University of New York Stony Brook.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Wharton1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Struhl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>RNA regulatory elements mediate control of <italic>Drosophila</italic> body pattern by the posterior morphogen nanos.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>955</fpage>
<lpage>967</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1720354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Murata1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Binding of pumilio to maternal hunchback mRNA is required for posterior patterning in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>80</volume>
<fpage>747</fpage>
<lpage>756</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7889568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Gamberi1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamberi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>An anterior function for the <italic>Drosophila</italic> posterior determinant Pumilio.</article-title>
<source>Development</source>
<volume>129</volume>
<fpage>2699</fpage>
<lpage>2710</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-AsaokaTaguchi1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asaoka-Taguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanyu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Maternal Pumilio acts together with Nanos in germline development in <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos.</article-title>
<source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>
<lpage>437</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Kadyrova1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadyrova</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Habara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Translational control of maternal Cyclin B mRNA by Nanos in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> germline.</article-title>
<source>Development</source>
<volume>134</volume>
<fpage>1519</fpage>
<lpage>1527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Zamore1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The Pumilio protein binds RNA through a conserved domain that defines a new class of RNA-binding proteins.</article-title>
<source>RNA</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>1421</fpage>
<lpage>1433</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9404893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Wharton2"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The Pumilio RNA-binding domain is also a translational regulator.</article-title>
<source>Mol Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>863</fpage>
<lpage>872</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Menon1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanyal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Habara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The translational repressor Pumilio regulates presynaptic morphology and controls postsynaptic accumulation of translation factor eIF-4E.</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>663</fpage>
<lpage>676</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15541314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Mee1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mee</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pym</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Regulation of neuronal excitability through pumilio-dependent control of a sodium channel gene.</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>8695</fpage>
<lpage>8703</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15470135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Ye1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Petritsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavis</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Nanos and Pumilio are essential for dendrite morphogenesis in <italic>Drosophila</italic> peripheral neurons.</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>314</fpage>
<lpage>321</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14972682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Schweers1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schweers</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> translational repressor pumilio regulates neuronal excitability.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>161</volume>
<fpage>1177</fpage>
<lpage>1185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Dubnau1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Barditch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gossweiler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The staufen/pumilio pathway is involved in <italic>Drosophila</italic> long-term memory.</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>286</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12593794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Steward1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Compartmentalized synthesis and degradation of proteins in neurons.</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>347</fpage>
<lpage>359</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14556713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Vessey1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vessey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaccani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Karra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Dendritic localization of the translational repressor Pumilio 2 and its contribution to dendritic stress granules.</article-title>
<source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>6496</fpage>
<lpage>6508</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Gerber1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Luschnig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasnow</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification of mRNAs associated with the translational regulator PUMILIO in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>4487</fpage>
<lpage>4492</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16537387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Recruitment of Nanos to hunchback mRNA by Pumilio.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>2704</fpage>
<lpage>2712</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10541556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Wang1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Modular recognition of RNA by a human pumilio-homology domain.</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>501</fpage>
<lpage>512</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Bernstein1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajarnavis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Opperman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Binding specificity and mRNA targets of a <italic>C. elegans</italic> PUF protein, FBF-1.</article-title>
<source>Rna</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>447</fpage>
<lpage>458</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15769874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-MacDonald1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>bicoid mRNA localization signal: Phylogenetic conservation of function and RNA secondary structure.</article-title>
<source>Development</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>161</fpage>
<lpage>171</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2081457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Stormo1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stormo</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Specificity, free energy and information content in protein-DNA interactions.</article-title>
<source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>109</fpage>
<lpage>113</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9581503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Stormo2"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stormo</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>DNA binding sites: Representation and discovery.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>16</fpage>
<lpage>23</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10812473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Dalby1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalby</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Discrete sequence elements control posterior pole accumulation and translational repression of maternal cyclin B RNA in <italic>Drosophila.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>EMBO J</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>1219</fpage>
<lpage>1227</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8458334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Heisenberg1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heisenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Mushroom body memoir: From maps to models.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>266</fpage>
<lpage>275</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12671643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Waddell1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>What can we teach <italic>Drosophila</italic>? What can they teach us?</article-title>
<source>Trends Genet</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>719</fpage>
<lpage>726</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11718926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Margulies1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubnau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Deconstructing memory in <italic>Drosophila.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>R700</fpage>
<lpage>R713</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139203</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-RuizCanada1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz-Canada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tejedor</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>DLG differentially localizes Shaker K&#x0002b;-channels in the central nervous system and retina of <italic>Drosophila.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>J Neurochem</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>1490</fpage>
<lpage>1501</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Connolly1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Associative learning disrupted by impaired Gs signaling in <italic>Drosophila</italic> mushroom bodies.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>274</volume>
<fpage>2104</fpage>
<lpage>2107</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8953046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Moore1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaruzelska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Firpo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Human Pumilio-2 is expressed in embryonic stem cells and germ cells and interacts with DAZ (Deleted in AZoospermia) and DAZ-like proteins.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>538</fpage>
<lpage>543</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Fox1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijo Pera</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Identification and characterization of RNA sequences to which human PUMILIO-2 (PUM2) and deleted in Azoospermia-like (DAZL) bind.</article-title>
<source>Genomics</source>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>105</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15607425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Nakahata1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakahata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagahama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Biochemical identification of <italic>Xenopus</italic> Pumilio as a sequence-specific cyclin B1 mRNA-binding protein that physically interacts with a Nanos homolog, Xcat-2, and a cytoplasmic polyadenylation element-binding protein.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>276</volume>
<fpage>20945</fpage>
<lpage>20953</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Gerber2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Extensive association of functionally and cytotopically related mRNAs with Puf family RNA-binding proteins in yeast.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>e79</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Cheong1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Engineering RNA sequence specificity of Pumilio repeats.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>13635</fpage>
<lpage>13639</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16954190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Opperman1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opperman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>A single spacer nucleotide determines the specificities of two mRNA regulatory proteins.</article-title>
<source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>945</fpage>
<lpage>951</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16244662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Sonoda2"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonoda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wharton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>
<italic>Drosophila</italic> Brain Tumor is a translational repressor.</article-title>
<source>Genes Dev</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>762</fpage>
<lpage>773</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Budnik1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hough</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Regulation of synapse structure and function by the <italic>Drosophila</italic> tumor suppressor gene <italic>dlg.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>627</fpage>
<lpage>640</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8893021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Guan1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kho</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorczyca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The <italic>Drosophila</italic> tumor suppressor gene, <italic>dlg,</italic> is involved in structural plasticity at a glutamatergic synapse.</article-title>
<source>Curr Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>695</fpage>
<lpage>706</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8793296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Chen1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Featherstone</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Discs-large (DLG) is clustered by presynaptic innervation and regulates postsynaptic glutamate receptor subunit composition in <italic>Drosophila.</italic>
</article-title>
<source>BMC Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15638945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Baines1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baines</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Neuronal homeostasis through translational control.</article-title>
<source>Mol Neurobiol</source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>113</fpage>
<lpage>121</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16215276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Lawrence1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Boguski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuwald</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Detecting subtle sequence signals: A Gibbs sampling strategy for multiple alignment.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>262</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8211139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-Clarke1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Labeling and purification of RNA synthesized by in vitro transcription.</article-title>
<source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>10</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10549510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pcbi.1000026-White1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore-Jarrett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruley</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>PUM2, a novel murine puf protein, and its consensus RNA-binding site.</article-title>
<source>RNA</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>1855</fpage>
<lpage>1866</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11780640</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>